<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A blast blown out of the north and ecchoing up towards the south to meet the cry of their oppressed brethren being a relation of some of the sufferings and other exercises of several of the people of God, in scorn called Quakers, in and about Richmond, Massam, Coverdale, Wensleydale, and Swaledale, and some others of the adjacent parts and places in the North Riding of the county of York since the beginning of the year 1660.</title>
            <author>R. R. (Richard Robinson), b. 1628?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1680</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 112 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57466</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1713</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6799</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13224403</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13224403</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98568</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57466)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98568)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 437:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A blast blown out of the north and ecchoing up towards the south to meet the cry of their oppressed brethren being a relation of some of the sufferings and other exercises of several of the people of God, in scorn called Quakers, in and about Richmond, Massam, Coverdale, Wensleydale, and Swaledale, and some others of the adjacent parts and places in the North Riding of the county of York since the beginning of the year 1660.</title>
                  <author>R. R. (Richard Robinson), b. 1628?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1680.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: R.R. [i.e., Richard Robinson]. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Friends' Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98568:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A BLAST blown out of the NORTH And Ecchoing up towards the SOUTH, To meet the CRY of their Oppreſſed Brethren.</p>
            <p>Being a Relation of ſome of the Sufferings and other Exerciſes of ſeveral of the People of God in ſcorn called <hi>Quakers</hi> in and about <hi>Richmond, Maſſam, Coverdale, Wenſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leydale</hi> and <hi>Swaledale,</hi> and ſome others of the adjacent Parts and Places in the <hi>North Riding</hi> of the County of <hi>York,</hi> ſince the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the year 1660.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Prov. 10. 7.</bibl> 
                  <hi>The Memory of the Juſt is Bleſſed; but the Name of the Wicked ſhall Rot.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Job 18. 7.</bibl> 
                  <hi>The Light ſhall be dark in his Tabernacle, and his Candle ſhall be put out with him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Verſ. 16.</bibl> 
                  <hi>His Roots ſhall be dryed up beneath, and above ſhall his Branch be cut off.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Verſ. 17.</bibl> 
                  <hi>His Remembrance ſhall periſh from the Earth, and he ſhall have no Name in the Street.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Verſ. 20.</bibl> 
                  <hi>They that come after him ſhall be aſtonied at his Day, as thoſe that went before were afrighted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Verſ. 21.</bibl> 
                  <hi>Surely ſuch are the Dwellings of the Wicked, and this is the Place of him that knoweth not God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Prov. 10. 23.</bibl> 
                  <hi>It is a Sport to a Fool to do Miſchief; but a Man of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding hath Wiſdom.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <bibl>Verſ. 25.</bibl> 
                  <hi>As the Whilewind paſſeth, ſo is the Wicked no more; but the Righteous is an Everlaſting Foundation.</hi>
               </p>
            </q>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1680.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98568:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98568:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>FRIEND;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THat part of this enſuing Treatiſe which relateth to the Sufferings of the Lord's People in Scorn cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Quakers,</hi> in the years 1670, and 1671. (hereafter mentioned) upon the <hi>Act</hi> entituled, <hi>An Act to prevent and ſuppreſs Seditious Conventicles,</hi> was for the moſt part of it ſave what is now altered by reaſon of Time and the Death of ſome of the Perſecutors, and other Matters) drawn up and made ready in or about the year 1671. or beginning of the year 1672. (as is remembred) and after ſeveral Examinations of the ſame, as to the Truth and Certainty thereof, was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for the <hi>Preſs;</hi> but the within-named <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> dying, and the within-named <hi>William Thorna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by</hi> the Informer removing to <hi>London,</hi> whereby the Perſecution of the ſaid People in that behalf and in thoſe Parts ſeemed to ceaſe, the Printing of what was ſo drawn up was for that time ſuſpended, &amp; the rather for that it was in the View and ſtood in the Faith and Belief of the <hi>Compiler</hi> of thoſe Papers, that there might be a further Opportunity rendred for that purpoſe; and that the within-named <hi>Joſeph Craddock (to the filling up of the meaſure of his former Wickedneſs)</hi> would (ere his Death) be concerned in the further
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98568:3"/>
Perſecution of ſome of the aforeſaid People, called <hi>Quakers,</hi> or ſome other ſuch like Wicked Act; and that the Compiler of the ſaid Papers might alſo come to be therein concerned, which thing is accordingly now come to paſs; for he is one of the Priſoners here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in after named: whereupon the aforeſaid Papers ſo drawn up, or the things therein contained upon a new review, with ſome Alterations and Additions of things not then known or come to hand, are thought good to be Printed, to which are alſo added and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the ſame joyned ſome former Sufferings and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes of the aforeſaid People, or ſome of them, as followeth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>R. R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98568:3"/>
            <head>A Blaſt blown out of the North, and Ecchoing Up Towards the South, to meet the Cry of their Oppreſſed Brethren.</head>
            <div type="history">
               <argument>
                  <p>A brief Relation of ſome of the Sufferings of ſome of the Lord's People in Scorn called <hi>Quakers,</hi> at and near <hi>Bellerby</hi> in the <hi>North Riding</hi> of the County of <hi>YORK,</hi> the 13th Day of the 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Moneth, in the Year 1660.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>UPon the ſaid day ſeveral of the ſaid people from ſeveral parts in and about <hi>Richmond, Maſſam, Coverdale,</hi> and ſome other of the adjacent Places, being met together at the Houſe of <hi>Ralph Ainſley</hi> in <hi>Bellerby</hi> aforeſaid, to wait upon and worſhip the Lord, two men came and called <hi>Ralph Ainſley,</hi> and told him, <hi>They had Order to break up the Meeting;</hi> but before Friends in the Houſe had any notice (for <hi>Ralph</hi> then being buſie ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up Horſes had not told them) there came divers Armed Men Ruſhing to the Door, crying, <hi>Where are theſe Rogues? We have Order to break up your Meeting;</hi> ſome of them ſaying, <hi>We will cut you as ſmall as Bread.</hi> Whereupon one of thoſe People ſo met, went to the Door to underſtand the Real Cauſe of their ſo coming, and whether they had any Order to hinder the ſaid peaceable Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or they in their own Wills had taken in hand to do it; who in Meekneſs ſpoke to them and told them, <hi>That they were there met
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98568:4"/>
in the Fear of the Lord, without the leaſt thought of Harm to any Creature.</hi> And another of the ſaid People, who were ſo met at the ſaid Houſe, being at the Door, ſpoke to ſome of them, deſiring <hi>to ſee their Order for ſo doing;</hi> and one of them drew his Sword, and ſaid, <hi>That was his Order:</hi> And their Fury was ſuch, that they would not hear what was in Soberneſs ſpoken to them, but fell a beating of them and other Friends; and after ſeveral had been beaten, one of the men ſaid, <hi>He would ſhew their Order;</hi> but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it could be read Friends were ſo hurryed and beat away, that none of them could either ſee the Extent of it, or tell from whom it came; only ſome of them ſaid, it came from <hi>William Dalton,</hi> one of the then Commiſſioners of the Militia. And while theſe things were thus doing at the Door (Friends in the Houſe not ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knowing the Matter, but what they might underſtand from the Noiſe and Tumult they heard) preſently came in ſome with Swords and Piſtols, and haled ſeveral forcibly out, and beat ſome of them, and haled ſome down to the Ground, to the ſhedding of Blood, whilſt others turned out their Horſes looſe into the Street, which by beating, pricking with Swords, ſhooting with Guns and Piſtols, the Owners had much ado to get their Horſes again, by means whereof divers Friends, after the breaking up of the ſaid Meeting, were prevented for ſome time of departing out of the Town: And ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral were beat in the Street with Swords and Staves, ſome bunched, ſome fired Guns and Piſtols charged with Powder at them, to the hurting of ſome of them. And ſome (beſides the Hurts themſelves ſuſtained) had their Hats and Clothes cut, ſome thrown down by the Hair of the Head, ſome ſtoned, and with luch like Uſage driven and hurryed away in a Violent and Bruitiſh Manner. And after they had been thus Hurryed, Beaten, Abuſed and Driven away, and were thereupon drawing Home-wards; as thoſe whoſe Way lay towards <hi>Marrick</hi> and <hi>Richmond</hi> were ſtaying and hovering one upon another, that they might ſee how each other did, or had eſcaped, and being about to part as their ſeveral Wayes lay towards their reſpective Dwellings, preſently ſome of the faſt Rude Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent People on Horſeback, and ſome on Foot, with Swords, Guns, Piſtols and Staves, came riding and running after them unto a <hi>Moore</hi> which lay in the Way, near a Mile from the Town aforeſaid, and there fell violently again upon them, ſtriking &amp; beating both Young
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98568:4"/>
and Old Men and Women in a moſt Inhuman and Cruel Manner, riding and running up and down, beating them, to the ſore hurting of many, and to the ſhedding of the Blood of ſome; for ſeveral were beat down to the Ground, inſomuch that ſome were for ſome time ſenſleſs, and not able of Body to remove till helped by others; yea, their Cruelty was ſuch, that they ſpared none, no, not young tender Maids, nor antient Women, but gave them ſeveral Blows, to the bruiſing of their Fleſh, making as it were even a Sport of ſuch Cruelty; all which to particularize, would be both too hard or difficult, and too tedious: Yet to the intent that ſuch a Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, ſo notoriouſly wicked and cruelly inflicted, without any juſt Cauſe or Provocation, upon an innocent People <hi>(for no other Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter but ſimply meeting together to wait upon and worſhip the One, True and Living God)</hi> may not wholly be caſt into Oblivion, I ſhall make mention of ſome, who being yet alive, and of good Report and Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit in their Generation, may be (if queried of) Witneſſes of the ſame, that is to ſay:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Whitton</hi> of <hi>Pattrick Brunton,</hi> when the Men came to the Door, threatning to break up the Meeting, upon deſiring to ſee their Order for ſuch Actings, one drew his Sword, and ſaid, <hi>That was his Order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Lofthouſe,</hi> now of <hi>Biſhopdale</hi> (then of <hi>Stainton)</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved ſeveral Blows on his Back, and had his Cloathes cut, and was caſt down by the Violence they uſed.</p>
               <p>His Son, <hi>Edward Lofthouſe,</hi> received ſeveral Strokes on his Back and Arms with a Sword and Pike-ſtaff, and a great Stroke on his Head with the Butt-end of a Muſquet or Fowling piece, beſides ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Thruſts with a Sword, running through his Cloathes, though not to the Wounding of his Body.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robert Goſling</hi> of <hi>Richmond</hi> (a tender man) was by the Violence of ſeveral Blows about his Head, Arms and Shoulders, with Staves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> beat down to the Ground, where for ſome time he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaved of Sence, and not able to Recover, till helped up by others; by reaſon of which Uſage, much Weakneſs hath ſince been, and yet is upon him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Phillip Swale</hi> of <hi>Hartford,</hi> a man well known unto many men of ſeveral Qualities, and of good Repute, being Serviceable in his
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98568:5"/>
Generation, received a ſore Blow on his Back with a Stone, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Blows on his Head and Back with a Sword.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Orton</hi> of <hi>Marvick,</hi> when he did go to take his Horſe, they beat him ſore with Swords, Pikes and Guns, that they much bruiſed his Arms and Shoulders; and when he led his Horſe away they beat him and his Horſe with much Cruelty; his Wife alſo was beaten.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>John Key</hi> (then alſo of <hi>Marvick)</hi> was beaten on the Moor with Swords and Staves, and puſhed with a Pike, that his Head, Arms and Shoulders were ſore bruiſed, and was twice beat to the Ground, in ſuch ſort that ſome who ſaw it, thought he ſhould never have riſen again.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſtopher Terry,</hi> now of <hi>Rippon,</hi> was beat in the Town and on the Moor, ſo that they fell'd him twice to the Ground, and his Head was cut, and it and other parts of his Body ſore bruiſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Beckwith</hi> had Powder ſhot in his face, that ſore hurt his Eyes.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anthony Raynold</hi> of <hi>Snape,</hi> as he was going away a man with a long Staff gave him ſeveral Blows, that he fell to the Ground, and after he was fallen did alſo beat him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Marmaduke Beckwith</hi> (now of <hi>High-Burton,</hi> and Brother of the afore-ſaid <hi>William Beckwith)</hi> going in the Town to get his Horſe, a Man in great Rage ſaid, <hi>Thou Dog, cannot thou ſpeak,</hi> and took him off the Ground by the Hair of the Head, and caſt him down at his Feet, and then Fudded him ſore with his Foot or Feet on his Head, both before and behind, that it ſwelled, and much Hair came off; and alſo fudded him in like manner on his Back.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mary Chaytor</hi> (of <hi>Richmond,</hi> afore-ſaid) received ſeveral Blows on her Arms, Neck and Back with a Staff, to the ſore bruiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and blackening of her Fleſh.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sarah Kirkby,</hi> then of the ſame place, received ſeveral Blows on her Arms with a Staff, and a ſore Blow on her Shoulder with a Muſquet or Fowling piece, by which Blows her Fleſh was ſore bruiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and blackened.</p>
               <p>But the Particularizing of ſo much Cruelty in ſuch an Aſſembly, being both too tedious, and alſo too difficult, what is before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned in that behalf ſhall ſuffice: only this know, that there were many others, both Men and Women (ſome whereof are dead,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98568:5"/>
others yet living) that might have been mentioned, and who ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered very cruelly at the hands of the aforeſaid Perſons, by being beat down, ſome till they lay ſenſleſs, ſtruck with Swords, Guns, Staves, and in a moſt inhumane manner; yea, many of them as cruelly (if not ſome more cruelly) than thoſe mentioned before, all which would be too tedious to relate, and that for no other Cauſe (as is before related) but only for meeting together to wait upon the Lord: Neither could they charge them with tho Breach of any juſt Law, nor had any words from them that might in the leaſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke them to this Cruelty, but in Meekneſs and Patience ſuffered what the other in their mad Fury were permitted to do unto them, rejoycing (as themſelves, or ſome of them teſtified) that they were counted worthy to ſuffer for his ſake, who in the dayes of his Humiliation ſuffered the Contradiction of Sinners; further alſo te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifying, that they wiſhed no Evil unto thoſe, by whom they thus ſuffered, but deſired they might come to ſee the Evil of their Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and Repent, and is not here made mention of or revived with intent to call the Parties therein concerned to an Account to their Prejudice; but only to the Intent that ſo cruel an Act of the Unrighteous, and patient Suffering of the Innocent and Harmleſs, may not be caſt into Oblivion, but left to Poſterity to judge, by the ſame in this behalf, of the Fruits of the True Spirit, and of the Falſe.</p>
               <p>In the ſame Year 1660. and in the 3d Moneth of that ſame Year, and as is ſuppoſed, about the ſame time, that the aforeſaid buſineſs at <hi>Bellerby</hi> was acted, came <hi>George Fawcett</hi> of <hi>Ballowfield</hi> in <hi>Wenſley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale,</hi> in the aforeſaid County of <hi>York,</hi> then a Chief Conſtable, with a Sword about him (being a rude Boiſterous kind of Young man) to <hi>Burton,</hi> in or near <hi>Biſhopdale</hi> in the <hi>North-Riding,</hi> of the aforeſaid County of <hi>York,</hi> bringing with him a Rude Wild Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of men, like himſelf, with Staves, Clubs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> where ſome of the People in Scorn called <hi>Quakers</hi> were peaceably met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, to wait upon and Worſhip the Lord, according to that Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtation of his Will diſcovered to them; and in a Rude and Boiſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous manner broke up their ſaid Meeting, and did Abuſe, Hale and Beat in or after a Violent Inhuman manner thoſe ſo met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and very Uncivilly, Boiſterouſly and Savagely behaved them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98568:6"/>
towards them; and particularly one among the reſt (to wit) <hi>John Hudſon</hi> of <hi>Burton</hi> aforeſaid, having, as is remembred, a long Hazle Staff in his hand, ſome-what in length reſembling a Hunting Pole, which, as is remembred, he took by the ſmall end in both his hands, and there-with he ſmote <hi>Samuel Watſon</hi> of <hi>Knight-ſtainforth</hi> (who was then among the aforeſaid People, ſo peaceably met toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to wait upon the Lord, as aforeſaid) ſo violently upon or about the Head, that with the Violence thereof, he (to wit) the ſaid <hi>Samuel</hi> fell to the Ground, and in that Condition for ſome conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able time lay as one in a manner dead, or bereaved of his Life, to the terrifying of thoſe who had ſo rudely behaved themſelves, and alſo of the doer thereof; and ſeveral of them began to ſhrink, or as it were draw back or aſide, and excuſe themſelves, as not having a hand in it, fearing as it ſhould ſeem, that he had been dead; but after he, through the Mercy of God was in ſome ſort recovered, they (to wit) the wild Company, returned to their former Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Behaviour and Deportment again, Hailing, Beating, Miſ-uſing, Punching, and Driving ſeveral of the ſaid People, ſo met as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, in a Barbarous, Inhumane and Uncivil manner out of the Town, not leaving them (as is remembred) until they ſet a great part of them ſome conſiderable ſpace out of the ſame, &amp; after they had a little left them (as is remembred) the ſaid <hi>Samuel</hi> going to Prayer, ſome of the aforeſaid Rude Company, came again, and in a Rude, Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>civil, Uncomely, Inhumane manner behaved themſelves towards the ſaid People, both Men and Women, which is now too hard to be particularized; only one <hi>William Farnaby</hi> drawing his Knife, cut ſeveral of the Horſes Bridles: And ſo after much Abuſe, having driven away the ſaid People, they (to wit) the rude Multitude depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, many of them Glorying in what they had ſo done; but the juſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venger of the Upright, who knows how to deliver the Righteous, and how to reſerve the Wicked to the day of Judgment to be puniſhed, though he may, and doth oft-times (as in this Caſe he did) ſpare long, and give a large time, yea, ſeveral Years to Repent in; yet if they will not Repent, and be Reconciled, ſo as the Lord may paſs by and Pardon them, and Heal them, he doth ſometimes bring them to become Examples of his Wrath, as may be obſerved in this man, (to wit) <hi>John Hudſon,</hi> who was the man that ſmote down the ſaid <hi>Samuel Watſon,</hi> who though he lived ſeveral Years after, yet going to <hi>Richmond</hi> about ſome Buſineſs in the Year 1678. in or about the 6th Moneth of the ſame Year, and about the 17th day of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98568:6"/>
that Moneth (as is remembred) and being going overthwart the Market-Place of the ſame Town, as though he intended to go to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Door of <hi>Anne Hopps,</hi> Widow, another man being with him, as he drew near the ſaid Door, ſuddainly he fell down flat upon his Face, and there finiſhed his days: The ſaid <hi>Anne Hopps,</hi> being by, who ſaw it, and gave the Relation of it, and was never by her ſeen more to move. And thus he (who ſome time before had in the Wickedneſs of his Mind ſmitten down an Innocent man, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any juſt Cauſe or Offence given or adminiſtered unto him, ſo that he lay for a conſiderable time as a man wholly dead, or without Life, yet by the Mercy of God was recovered) was by the hand of the ſame juſt God (againſt whom he had ſinned in this behalf) ſmitten down, ſo that he never roſe again; which may be a Caveat, and ought to give Warning to all men of what Degree or Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſoever they be of, to beware and have a care what they do, and how they behave themſelves; for though the Lord by many may be looked upon, <hi>as one that delayes his coming,</hi> yet at laſt he may be expected to come unto ſuch, and when he comes his Reward is with him, to give unto every man ſuitably, as his Works ſhall be; Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation and Anguiſh to every Soul that doth not Righteouſly; but Peace and Joy to the Upright in Heart: So while there is a time let all men prize it.</p>
               <p>Upon the 31th Day of the 6th Moneth, called <hi>Auguſt,</hi> in the Year 1662. being the firſt Day of the Week, came <hi>James Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calfe</hi> of <hi>Nappa,</hi> in the Country of <hi>York,</hi> and then in the Commiſſion of Peace to the Door of <hi>James Wetherald</hi> in <hi>Askrigg</hi> in the ſame County, where ſome of the People of God in Scorn called <hi>Quakers</hi> were peaceably met together, only to wait upon and worſhip the One, True and Living God in Spirit and Truth, according to his will and thoſe manifeſtations of him they had received. And though he the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> had often known or heard of their ſo peaceably meeting together at that place before that time, and for no other purpoſe ſave only (as aforeſaid) to wait upon and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the Lord; yet to the intent to render the ſaid People more O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious or Dangerous, or elſe to render his Appearance the more Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, he brought with him a great Company of Armed men; and being on this wiſe come to the Door of the ſaid Houſe, they cauſed
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98568:7"/>
Friends by the ſaid Armed men to be had out, and brought before them; where upon Promiſe made to appear before the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> the next day, they were all, ſave <hi>Richard Robinſon,</hi> let go, and him the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> committed to the Cuſtody of <hi>Richard Beſſon</hi> of the ſame <hi>Askrigg,</hi> then Conſtable, who let him go Home alſo: and coming again the next day, the ſaid <hi>James Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calfe</hi> committed Nineteen of them to the Common Jayle at <hi>York,</hi> and Four to the Houſe of Correction, until the next Quarter Seſſions of the Peace, to be held for the <hi>North-Riding</hi> of the ſaid County of <hi>York.</hi> But by the Kindneſs of the ſaid Conſtable, <hi>Rich. Beſſon,</hi> to whoſe Charge they were committed, they were ſtayed at Home moſt part of a Moneth; and then through the Threatnings of the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe,</hi> ſent to Priſon until the ſaid Seſſions, where, after much Diſcourſe, thoſe Perſons here after-named, with others, were fined, and the Fines levied as followeth.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Richard Robinſon</hi> of <hi>Counterſett</hi> in <hi>Wenſleydale</hi> was fined 2 l. for which he had a Mare diſtrained by <hi>Chriſtopher Todd</hi> of <hi>Middleham, Edmond Blades</hi> and <hi>Bartholomew Blades</hi> of <hi>Askrigg,</hi> aforeſaid, or ſome of them, about the 3d day of the 11th Moneth, in the Year 1662. worth, by the Owner's Eſtimation of her, 3 l. 6 s. 8 d.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richard Rowth</hi> of <hi>Hawes</hi> was fined 10s. for which the aforeſaid Perſons, or ſome of them, did diſtrain and take a Cow, at or about the ſame time, worth about 3l. 10s.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bartholomew Harryſon</hi> of <hi>Counterſett</hi> and <hi>Iſabell</hi> his Wife, being fined either of them 12d. had diſtrained for the ſame by the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Perſons, or ſome of them, about the time aforeſaid, ſome Cloth and Apparel; but the ſame was releaſed by a Neighbour, and returned back again, only the party got ſome other Commodities, and ſtayed ſo much as the Fines came to, in Payment for the ſame.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>James Gurnell</hi> of <hi>Marſett,</hi> fined 10s. had four Pewter Diſhes and one Riding-Coat diſtrained, and taken for the ſame, by the aforeſaid <hi>Edmond</hi> and <hi>Bartholomew Blaydes,</hi> the 13th day of the Moneth aforeſaid, worth about 1l. 9s.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mary Lambert</hi> of <hi>Busk</hi> fined 10 s. had Stockings diſtrained and taken for the ſame, by the aforeſaid <hi>Edmond</hi> and <hi>Bartholomew Blaydes,</hi> worth about 12 s.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98568:7"/>
                  <hi>There were ſeveral other Perſons at that time fined, beſides what is before-mentioned, ſo that the Fines in all came to 19 l. 13 s. But whether any of the Reſidue was diſtrained for or no, I know not.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="history">
               <argument>
                  <p>Now followeth an Account of ſome of the Sufferings, and other Exerciſes of ſeveral of the ſaid People of God in Scorn called <hi>Quakers,</hi> which hath happened unto them ſince the beginning of the Year 1670. in and about <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond, Maſſam,</hi> and ſome of the adjacient Parts, and <hi>Dales,</hi> within the <hi>North Riding</hi> of the aforeſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>York,</hi> occaſioned by the Proceedings of <hi>Joſeph Craddock,</hi> now living, and <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> deceaſed: Together with ſome few others in the Commiſſion of Peace, within the ſaid <hi>Riding;</hi> and alſo by the Proceedings of the Mayor and Recorder of the ſaid Town of <hi>Richmond,</hi> upon the Information of <hi>William Thornaby</hi> the Elder, Inn keeper of the aforeſaid <hi>Richmond,</hi> and late one of the Serjeants there (but caſt out of that Place for his Evil Carriage and Miſdemeanours) together with his Son, and other Agents and Emiſaries of his, who being given up to Spoil and Deſtruction, did with Covetouſneſs ſeek after their Neighbours Goods, and did greedily endeavour to catch them by any means, not regarding what became of the Owners, ſo they could but get their Prey; taking their oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion by, and Encouragement thereunto from the late <hi>Act of Parliament,</hi> Entituled, <hi>An Act to Prevent and Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Seditious Conventicles,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </argument>
               <p>FRom which (I ſay) according to that Conſtruction, they paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon it, and Uſe they have made of it, ſuch Looſe and Diſſolute Perſons, as the ſaid <hi>Thornaby,</hi> being a man of a deſperate Condition, hath been Emboldened under the Notion of <hi>An Informer
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98568:8"/>
for the King,</hi> to commit ſuch Groſs and Horrid Villanies, as in the times of a more Sober and <hi>Chriſtian-</hi>like Diſpenſation or Diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Law and Juſtice, could be looked on by Sober and Diſcreet Perſons (as it is by ſuch at this day, whoſe Hearts have been ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded to ſee it) to be no leſs than Theft and Robbery: And that <hi>Act</hi> (according to that Conſtruction they have paſſed upon (and uſe they have made of it) no better or other than a Cloak for ſuch to Act by or under; who would have acted as badly before, but that they feared Puniſhment by a Law; nay, ſome known Thieves condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning their Doings in this behalf, diſdaining to act ſo groſly upon an Innocent Harmleſs People, as they (in this Caſe) did upon us, being Encouraged thereunto, as will appear by the Sequel of this Diſcourſe, which is no other than Truth, and not all that might be truly ſaid of their Evil Actions in this behalf neither) by ſuch whoſe Endeavours ſhould have been to Suppreſs Vice and Encourage them that do Well; for to this end only ſhould the Magiſtrate bear his Sword, and not to ſet up and carry on the Intereſt of Falſe Swearers, and other Injurious Perſons, whoſe Proceedings in this behalf they Countenanced and Encouraged, under pretence of putting that Act in Execution, made (as appears by the <hi>Title</hi> and <hi>Preamble</hi> thereof) <hi>To Prevent and Suppreſs Seditious Conventicles</hi> (Only) <hi>and to provide a more speedy Remedy againſt the growing and dangerous Practices of Seditious Sectaries, and other Diſloyal Perſons,</hi> &amp;c. And if made only for ſuch as are Dangerous, Seditious, Diſloyal, Contrivers of Inſurrections and Plotters, and ſuch as are only Pretenders to Tender Conſcience (but are not really Conſcientious) and for ſuch as are Diſturbers and Breakers of the Peace, according as the ſame ought to be; then not for Peaceable Harmleſs People, ſuch as the Harmleſs People called <hi>Quakers</hi> are, and have been, who make, and have made it their Endeavours only to Serve, Wait upon and Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip the One, True and Living God in Spirit and Truth Really; and not in or under a pretence only of Religious Exerciſe, do they meet together under that Pretence, to Plot or Contrive Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, neither to ſtir up any Sedition, or Diſturb or break the Peace, or offer Violence to any, as Experience on their behalf doth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who have given their Cheeks to the Smiter, and their Heads to them that have plucked off the Hair, not anſwering again. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther is it to be believed that a <hi>Chriſtian-Parliament</hi> (and ſuch the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98568:8"/>
                  <hi>Parliament of England</hi> would be thought to be) who are guided in the Counſel, Wiſdom and Fear of the Lord, and therein direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, will ever make Laws to limit the Lord God to this or that Form, or to this or that Way of Worſhip, and that he ſhall either be Served and Worſhipped in ſuch a Way as they have preſcribed, that is to ſay, according to the <hi>Liturgy of the Church of England</hi> (the Inventions of men) or he muſt not be ſerved at all; for this were to limit the holy One of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and to make God, even the Living God, Subordinate to Sinful Man; but rather to let him have his Liberty to be ſerved and worſhipped as he will, and in what way he moſt delighteth and chuſeth; <hi>For doth not the Wind blow where it liſteth, and thou heareſt the ſound thereof, but neither knowſt from whence it is, nor whither it goes? and ſo are all they that are born of the Spirit:</hi> And therefore not to be reſtrained under great Mulcts and Puniſhments; for this was never the Practice of the People of God in any Age, but the contrary. Neither can they which practiſe ſuch things now claim any Intereſt or Part with the People of God in this Age, nor in the Scriptures of Truth, and Writings of the Prophets and Holy men of God, who were never Perſecutors, but on the contrary were Perſecuted, even as it is at this day; <hi>He that lives after the Fleſh Perſecutes him that lives after the Spirit.</hi> And therefore, I ſay, in <hi>Chriſtian Charity</hi> (conſidering they pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed themſelves to be <hi>Chriſtians</hi> that made it) might the ſaid Act (if we did not know their Intent in making it) be looked on only to concern Seditious, Turbulent, Unruly, Peace-breaking Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whoſe Actions demonſtrate them to be ſo; and only to be made and intended for ſuch, rather than for Harmleſs Innocent Self-denying People, ſuch as the Innocent People called <hi>Quakers</hi> are, and have been; whoſe Endeavours (I ſay) both now, and at all times, ever ſince they were a People, have been, and yet are, <hi>To keep a Conſcience void of Offence, both towards God, and towards Man;</hi> and not to Plot and Contrive Inſurrections: Neither have our Meetings been, or yet are a Terror to the People among whom we live or reſide, and have our Converſe, they being gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally otherwiſe perſwaded of us, and know or believe us to be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe minded; yet againſt &amp; upon us in particular (&amp; that to the diſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the good People in this part of the Nation, among whom we live) hath the Force of the ſaid <hi>Act</hi> been put in Execution, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98568:9"/>
the ſaid <hi>Thornaby</hi> employed himſelf, his Son, and other his Agents and Emiſaries, as <hi>Informers,</hi> to ſubvert and deſtroy the Eſtates of many.</p>
               <p>And as a beginning to his Actions, he the ſaid <hi>Thornaby,</hi> together with one <hi>Matthew Chawder</hi> of <hi>Reeth</hi> in <hi>Swaledale,</hi> in the County and Riding aforeſaid, upon the 15th of the 3d moneth, called <hi>May,</hi> in the year 1670. <hi>(he the ſaid</hi> Thornaby <hi>having the ſame day been at</hi> Richmond <hi>Meeting)</hi> did come to the Houſe of one <hi>Elizabeth Cherry</hi> Widow in <hi>Swaledale</hi> aforeſaid, where finding to the number of <hi>Seven Perſons (beſides thoſe of the Family)</hi> of the aforeſaid Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple called <hi>Quakers,</hi> met together to wait upon and worſhip the <hi>One True and Living God in Spirit and Truth, according to his Will,</hi> they the ſaid <hi>Thornaby</hi> and <hi>Chawder</hi> the <hi>Informers</hi> went to the before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>named <hi>James Metcalfe;</hi> and ſwore to the number of <hi>Seventeen Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons;</hi> by which it may eaſily be perceived, <hi>what manner of Perſons employ themſelves as Informers, which ought not, neither heretofore have been thought worthy to go unpuniſhed.</hi> And as a further Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of their wilful and deſperate Wickedneſs and Perjury, at the ſame time ſwore, <hi>That one</hi> Thomas Kipling <hi>was then at the ſaid Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting;</hi> who the ſame Day and at or about the ſame Hour was at <hi>Newcaſtle upon Tine,</hi> about Thirty Five Miles from the ſaid <hi>Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth Cherry</hi>'s Houſe (as was after proved.) And further alſo ſwore at the ſame time, <hi>That</hi> Richard Robinſon <hi>of</hi> Healaugh Park <hi>in</hi> Swaledale <hi>aforeſaid, was then alſo there.</hi> And when the ſaid <hi>Thornaby</hi> came about ten dayes after to diſtrain the Goods and Chattels of the ſaid <hi>Richard Robinſon,</hi> for a Fine of 5 s. by their ſaid Oathes impoſed upon him, he confeſſed openly, <hi>He had never ſeen the Face of him the ſaid</hi> R. R. <hi>before;</hi> and ſo in effect confeſſed himſelf Forſworn, &amp; gave his own Oath the Lye (as it well deſerved) for the ſaid <hi>R. R.</hi> was not at the ſaid Houſe when the ſaid <hi>Thornaby</hi> was there, as was alſo proved. Likewiſe they the ſaid <hi>Thornaby</hi> and <hi>Chawder</hi> further ſwore at the ſame time againſt <hi>William Orton</hi> and <hi>John Key,</hi> then both of <hi>Marrick,</hi> for Preaching and Teaching in the ſaid Aſſembly; whereas upon an Appeal made by the ſaid <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Orton</hi> and <hi>John Key,</hi> upon the Diſtreſs of their Goods and Chattels taken for the Fines of 20 l. apiece impoſed upon them by reaſon of the ſaid Oaths, it was plainly proved there were no Words ſpoken by the ſaid <hi>William Orton</hi> and <hi>John Key;</hi> or either of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98568:9"/>
them, in way of Preaching or Teaching; but what was ſpoken, was ſpoken in way of Diſcourſe between the ſaid <hi>William Orton</hi> and <hi>John Key</hi> on the one part, and the ſaid <hi>Thornaby</hi> and his Agents on the other part: Nevertheleſs the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> upon the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and Oathes aforeſaid, without any other manner of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction, and without calling or ſummoning the Parties accuſed to appear and anſwer perſonally before him according to Law, did iſſue forth a Warrant, whereby he gave power to the Conſtables, Churchwardens (ſo called) and Overſeers, to diſtrain for the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Fines impoſed by him on the ſaid <hi>Seventeen Perſons,</hi> ſo reported by the aforeſaid falſe Information to be at the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Cherry</hi>'s Houſe. And leſt he the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> ſhould come ſhort in Wickedneſs, or otherwiſe, that he might gratifie the Informers, he directed his Warrant to the Conſtables, Churchwardens and Overſeers, and more eſpecially to the ſaid <hi>Thornaby,</hi> whom he terms a <hi>Gentleman,</hi> and <hi>Chawder,</hi> whom he calls a <hi>Yeoman,</hi> giving unto them thereby alſo power to diſtrain as well as the other, and alſo more SPECIAL Power, inaſmuch as the Warrant was more eſpecially directed to them; although that very <hi>Act</hi> by which they did pretend to proceed, doth give the Power of Diſtreſs only and joyntly to the <hi>Conſtables, Churchwardens and Overſeers,</hi> and to no other: <hi>And the Appointment of One, is the Excluſion of Another,</hi> according to that Rule or Maxim in Law, <hi>Deſignatio unius eſt excluſio alterius;</hi> as when an <hi>Act of Parliament</hi> (which is the Introduction of a Novel Law (as this is) giveth the Power and Intereſt to one certain perſon, by that expreſs Deſignation of one, all others are excluded: for 'tis a further Ground in Law, <hi>Expreſſum facit ceſſare tacitum; That which is expreſſed makes that which is implyed to ceaſe.</hi> Read <hi>Hawkes</hi> his Grounds of the Laws, fol. 448, and 466. <hi>Cooke</hi>'s Comm. fol. 183. <hi>Ployd.</hi> 106. <hi>Stradling</hi>'s Caſe. And alſo further by the ſaid Warrant in the King's Name commands them to diſtrain the Goods and Chattels of the aforeſaid <hi>Richard Robinſon</hi> for a Fine of 5 s. impoſed by him the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe,</hi> upon the ſaid <hi>Richard Robinſon,</hi> under pretence that the Wife of the ſaid <hi>Richard</hi> was at the aforeſaid Meeting; againſt whom the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> had no Information, neither did ſhe ſtand Convicted before him. And here all may ſee what manner of Man the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> was, and whether fit to be in the <hi>Commiſſion of Peace</hi> or no, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98568:10"/>
what he would have done, if not reſtrained by a more ſecret Hand: For if the Law, by which, in this behalf, he pretended to proceed, were not ſtrict enough to anſwer His Will, and the <hi>Informers</hi> Ends; he would (as in this Caſe he did) add to it, to make it worſe: And whether theſe things be according to Juſtice, and conducing to the Honour and Reputation of the King, his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Parliament, and to the Advancement of his Intereſt in theſe Nations, let the Wife in Heart judge: And whether they which act ſuch things could or can be truly ſaid to be the <hi>King's Friends, and to Love and Honour him, and ſeek the Conſervation and Advancement of his Intereſt and Government,</hi> who ſo groſly and in the Face of a wiſe People <hi>Abuſe him</hi> (who is ſaid to be <hi>The Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of Juſtice,</hi> and <hi>ſhould Act no <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt Thing)</hi> by ſending forth ſuch Warrants in his Name, and acting ſuch things under the Notion of his Authority, as are quite contrary to Law, and conducing very much to the <hi>Subverſion of Juſtice, Truth and Righteouſneſs;</hi> which things flouriſhing and abounding in any Kingdom, cauſes <hi>Happineſs,</hi> and <hi>gives Satisfaction to the Good People thereof;</hi> but being ſubverted and turned backward (as in this Caſe) many times brings Ruin: But the afore-mentioned Proceedings, Falſe Oathes and Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, being in part laid before and preſented to the view of ſome more Eminent Perſons <hi>(Members of the then Parliament)</hi> who appeared Haters and Deteſtors of ſuch Illegal and Unjuſt Proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, and from whom better Returns of Juſtice was expected) their Advice was, <hi>To indict the ſaid</hi> Thornaby <hi>and</hi> Chawder <hi>of Perjury,</hi> which being accordingly done, the ſaid <hi>Chawder,</hi> knowing himſelf guilty, Fled; but <hi>Thornaby</hi> being an <hi>Impudent Perſon,</hi> appeared at the next <hi>General Quarter-Seſſions of the Peace</hi> for the ſaid Riding, held at <hi>Richmond,</hi> where the <hi>Grand Jury,</hi> upon Evidence ſworn and examin'd, found the <hi>Indictments</hi> (there being two) againſt <hi>Thornaby;</hi> whereupon the ſaid <hi>Thornaby,</hi> by the Advice of <hi>Joſeph Craddock</hi> and one <hi>William Robinſon</hi> alſo in the <hi>Commiſſion of Peace,</hi> who it ſeems feared the Juſtice of ſome then preſent, did put in his <hi>Traverſe</hi> to the ſaid <hi>Indictments,</hi> they or the one of them promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing him <hi>All the Favour the Court could ſhew him;</hi> and further told him, <hi>That if he did not Traverſe the ſaid Indictments, Ignominy would follow,</hi> or to that purpoſe; whereupon he was bound over to <hi>traverſe</hi> the ſaid <hi>Indictments</hi> at the next <hi>Quarter-Seſſions of the Peace</hi>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:98568:10"/>
for the ſaid Riding, which was holden at <hi>Thursk</hi> in the ſaid Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; where it was the Endeavours of ſome then preſent <hi>(who may ſince have ſeen the Bad Effects of that Action of theirs)</hi> to quaſh the <hi>Indictments,</hi> which they did for ſome Defect (as was pretended) in Form; nevertheleſs, it was aſſented unto, <hi>That</hi> Thornaby <hi>ſhould be indicted again at the next Seſſions;</hi> which being effected, and the <hi>Indictments</hi> preferred, and the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> ſworn, and <hi>Grand Jury</hi> alſo, who was gone forth to examin the <hi>Witneſſes</hi> in order to the finding of <hi>Thornaby</hi> Guilty or Not Guilty; whick <hi>Joſeph Crad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock</hi> knowing, who had ſeen the <hi>Indictments,</hi> and knew them to be punctually proved, together with <hi>James Metcalfe,</hi> at the Inſtance of the ſaid <hi>Thornaby,</hi> ſent for the ſaid <hi>Indictments</hi> to the <hi>Grand Jury,</hi> who not knowing their Intent in ſending for them, did ſend the ſame accordingly unto the ſaid <hi>Joſeph Craddock</hi> and <hi>James Metcalfe,</hi> who kept them, and would not return them back again, nor ſuffer the ſaid <hi>Thornaby</hi> to come to his Tryal, nor the <hi>Grand Jury</hi> to proceed and diſcharge themſelves of that Oath, which but a little before the Court had impoſed upon them, touching <hi>Thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naby</hi>'s Tryal; neither would they deliver the <hi>Indictments</hi> to thoſe that paid for them, and who ſuffered by <hi>Thornaby</hi>'s Falſe Oaths; <hi>but by all Means, like the</hi> Jews <hi>of old, ſought how to deliver or free</hi> Barrabas, <hi>and give up</hi> Truth <hi>unto Suffering:</hi> For when <hi>Juſtice was deſired according to Law,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Joſeph Craddock</hi> domineeringly began to <hi>accuſe Friends of Malice for proſecuting of</hi> Thornaby; though ſuch as ſuffer <hi>(as thoſe who proſecuted in this behalf had done, having their Goods taken from them by reaſon of the ſaid Falſe Oathes)</hi> have always and at all times in the Laws of <hi>England,</hi> and by the Impartial and Unbyaſſed Miniſters thereof, been thought worthy and been adjudged to have Juſt Cauſe to complain, for to redreſs and remedy Wrongs and Injuries, and to puniſh Offenders and Perjuries, and to Anſwer all Juſt Complaints was the ſaid Law pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided; and ſuch Complainings and Proceedings, whether by In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictment or otherwiſe, howſoever grounded upon a real Suffering (as in this Caſe it was) have not heretofore, neither at this time honeſtly can be accounted <hi>Malice,</hi> eſpecially in ſo weighty a Matter as that is, wherein <hi>Life, Liberty</hi> and <hi>Eſtate</hi> is concern'd, and eſpecially <hi>when the Puniſhment deſired and endeavoured to be inflicted upon the Offender, for his Falſe Oath (though it be of Dangerous
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98568:11"/>
Conſequence to all men) is no other or greater than ſimply ſuch as may diſable and ſtop him from wilfully ſinning againſt his own Soul, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperately running into thoſe Evils which are of bad Conſequence both before God and Man.</hi> But on the contrary, <hi>Malice</hi> is not hid in ſuch, who contrary to their <hi>Duty</hi> and <hi>Oath</hi> deny or defer to do Juſtice upon Offenders, yea, even in Criminal Cauſes for the King, becauſe of their particular Envy to them which proſecute. And as a farther Evidence of his Evil Will and Deſire of Ruin to the Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferers; or otherwiſe, to the Intent to render them more odious, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to get a Cloak for his illegal Proceedings; he the ſaid <hi>Joſeph Craddock</hi> further upon the Bench ſaid, <hi>That if they</hi> (to wit, the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers) had Power, they would Cut all their Throats:</hi> which Report of his, as it is moſt Falſe, ſo it gained him as little Credit, the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple generally before whom he ſpoke it being otherwiſe perſwaded of us, as a people that had known our Deportments better than to believe ſuch Lyes. But on the contrary, he the ſaid <hi>Joſeph Crad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock,</hi> together with the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe,</hi> and all others that joyned with them in this Buſineſs, did more plainly make it appear, that they ſought the Loſs, Ruin and Deſtruction of the <hi>Quakers,</hi> and not only of them, but by theſe Examples leave a Gap open, which being entred in at, may tend to the Ruin and Deſtruction of all Men, of what Degree or Condition ſoever. For if <hi>Perjury</hi> may eſcape, and go unpuniſhed, and be Tolerated, Encouraged and Protected in one man; by the ſame Rule, and with as good Authority may it (to wit, <hi>Perjury)</hi> be Tolerated and Encouraged in every man; and if by Falſe Swearing they may Rob one Man of his Goods, by the ſame Rule, and with as good Authority may they do it to another; and hereby no man comes to be ſafe either in Life or Eſtate: for if the Law, which is or ſhould be the Guard of every man's Life, Liberty and Eſtate, be broken upon one, by the ſame Rule, and with as good Authority, may it be broken up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all; and then what is become of thoſe good and wholſome Laws, heretofore made for the Protection of Men in their Lives, Liberties and Eſtates, and for the Puniſhment of Tranſgreſſors and Falſe Swearers? or were they made for ſome, and not for others, and ſo conſequently againſt ſome, and not againſt others, according to the Wills and Fancies of the Miniſters thereof? Was not, nay is not Juſtice to be done to all the King's Subjects, without Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98568:11"/>
of Perſons? Read the Oath appointed for all the Juſtices, <hi>Raſtal,</hi> fol. 244, and 245. <hi>Mag. Char.</hi> Chap. 29. Stat. <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. Chap. 4. <hi>Raſtal,</hi> 332. Nay, <hi>Though Letters or Commandments ſhould come from the King to the contrary, yet were they to go forth to do Juſtice, notwithſtanding ſuch Letters and Commandments.</hi> And are not the ſame Laws in force yet? if not, ſhew us when repealed, and when there was a Law made for Judges and Juſtices in ſuch Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes to deny and defer to men Juſtice and Right, as here in the Caſe of <hi>Thornaby</hi> Juſtice and Right was both denyed and deferred; and ſo in effect the ſaid <hi>Joſeph Craddock,</hi> and the reſt that joyned with him in protecting <hi>Thornaby,</hi> are become more guilty than the <hi>Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers,</hi> of that which he ſlanderouſly endeavoured to caſt upon them, that is to ſay, <hi>Cutting of Throats,</hi> or <hi>Taking of Life.</hi> For if what the Learned <hi>Cooke</hi> ſaith in <hi>Adams</hi> and <hi>Lambert</hi>'s Caſe, be true, viz <hi>Panis pauperum, vita pauperum et qui, defraudat eos vir ſanguinis eſt;</hi> Then <hi>Joſeph Craddock</hi> and <hi>James Metcalfe,</hi> and all others who joyned with them in protecting <hi>Thornaby</hi> from coming to condign Puniſhment for his Falſe Oathes, and thereby encoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged him to perſevere in his ſaid Wicked Practices, to the Taking, Spoiling and Deſtroying of his Poor and Harmleſs Neighbours Goods, to the diſabling ſome of them to get competent Suſtenance for themſelves and Children, and that without Juſt Cauſe, will have much ado to clear themſelves from being Men of Blood, or Blood<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guilty or Blood-thirſty Men. And here by the Protecting of <hi>Thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naby</hi> in his ſaid Perjury (as well as in other Caſes) it may plainly be perceived, <hi>That it was not ſo much</hi> Joſeph Craddock <hi>and</hi> James Metcalfe'<hi>s Zeal to put the Laws in Execution, and increaſe the King's Revenue by getting of Fines, and his Honour by diſtributing Juſtice impartially, that made them ſo forward, as it was their Envy and Evil Will againſt the</hi> Quakers, <hi>ſo called; for if it had, they would have done Juſtice upon</hi> Thornaby <hi>for his Falſe Oathes, according to Law; 5 Eliz.</hi> chap. 9. 14 <hi>Eliz.</hi> chap. 11. and not have protected Falſe Swearers under the Notion of doing Service for the King, who is Diſhonoured by ſuch Services, and his Name Abuſed by ſuch Applications; neither would they have hindred the King of ſuch a Conſiderable Sum of Money, as upon proof of the ſaid Perjury had been due unto him by the ſaid Law. But I may truly
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98568:12"/>
ſay, <hi>Juſtice is turned backward, and Equity cannot enter;</hi> for if it could, Falſe Oaths and Perjury would not be made the Inſtruments of ruining men in their Eſtates, as in this Caſe they were and have been. And now whether ſuch Actions, and the Proceedings be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore mentioned, were not and are Dangerous Practices, and of Bad Conſequence, againſt the growing and encreaſing Evils; whereof a prudent Parliament had more need to provide a ſpeedy Remedy, than againſt the Peaceable Meetings of the Lord's Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; let the Wiſe in Heart judge. For by the latter God is Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, his Name and Power Exalted and Magnified, his Truth Spread and Increaſed; and by the Protection, Toleration and En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement thereof the Kingdom and Government may expect to be Bleſſed and Eſtabliſhed: But by the former, as God is Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured, ſo the King and his Authority is Abuſed, his Laws Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated, his Subjects Ruined, and their Liberties Infringed, and therefore have need to be remedied. For it is an antient but ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Rule or Maxime, <hi>Salus populi ſuprema lex;</hi> i. e. <hi>The Safety of the People is the chiefeſt Law.</hi> But this ſeems with theſe men and in this matter to be laid waſte or diſregarded, while the Hedge, which the Law ſets for the Protection of every man's Life, Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Eſtate, comes thus to be thrown down, and laid open for every Wild Bore and Ravenous Beaſt, ſuch as the ſaid <hi>Thornaby,</hi> even as it were the very Scum and Off-ſcouring of men, by Falſe Oaths or otherwiſe, to enter in, root up and lay waſte the Rights and Intereſts of Honeſt, Harmleſ, Self-denying People, ſuch as the Law in it ſelf principally delights to honour, and for whoſe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Protection the ſame Law appears to have been chiefly made: For even upon theſe Encouragements, and the Oaths and Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the ſaid <hi>Thornaby</hi> and other his Agents and Emiſaries were all thoſe Goods taken, and Spoil enſuing made, moſt whereof by Warrants from <hi>Joſeph Craddock</hi> and <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, and by <hi>Thomas Craddock</hi> and <hi>John Bartlett</hi> in <hi>Richmond;</hi> for no other Offence but only for peaceably meeting together, ſimply to wait upon and worſhip the One, True &amp; living God in Spirit and Truth according to his Will, <hi>and not for Plotting or Contriving In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrections, neither for any Sedition or Dangerous Practices;</hi> theſe or any of them being not ſo much as by the ſaid <hi>Informers,</hi> or any of them, laid to their Charge.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:98568:12"/>
And <hi>firſt,</hi> Taken from the before-ntioned <hi>Richard Robinſon</hi> of <hi>Healaugh Park</hi> in <hi>Swaledale</hi> by Warrant from the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe,</hi> grounded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> falſe Oaths and Informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of <hi>William Thornaby, Matthew Chawder,</hi> for a Fine of 5 s. impoſed upon himſelf, who was proved not to be at the ſaid Meeting when <hi>Thornaby</hi> and <hi>Chawder</hi> were there; and for a Fine of 5 s. for his Wife, againſt whom <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> had no Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, neither did ſhe ſtand convicted before him, yet by his Warrant did <hi>Henry Watſon</hi> Conſtable, and <hi>William Thornaby,</hi> (about the twenty fifth day of the third moneth, 1670.) take Pewter from the ſaid <hi>Richard Robinſon,</hi> worth about 19 s.</p>
               <p>By the ſame Warrant did the ſame Conſtable, at or about the ſame time, diſtrain and take from <hi>Robert Addeſon</hi> of <hi>Healy,</hi> three Pewter Platters and one Braſs Pot, worth about 12 s.</p>
               <p>And about the ſame time did the ſame Conſtable and Informer, by the ſaid Warrant, diſtrain a Mare of one <hi>Nicholas Rawes</hi> in <hi>Swaledale</hi> aforeſaid, for a Fine of 5 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> impoſed upon him, worth about 2 l. 10 s.</p>
               <p>Alſo the ſame Conſtable, about the ſame time, and by the ſame Warrant, did diſtrain and take from <hi>Simon Harker</hi> of <hi>Swaledalc</hi> aforeſaid, for a Fine of 5 s. one Braſs Pot, worth about 7 s.</p>
               <p>Upon the 22d day of the 3d Moneth, called <hi>May,</hi> 1670. did <hi>William Thornaby,</hi> Elder, and <hi>Henry Spence,</hi> both of <hi>Richmond,</hi> Informers together, with <hi>James Metcalf</hi> of <hi>Bainbrigg,</hi> Conſtable, and one <hi>Robert Jackſon</hi> of the ſame place, came to the Houſe of <hi>Thomas Fawcett</hi> of <hi>Hawes</hi> in <hi>Wenſleydale,</hi> where finding ſome of the aforeſaid People called <hi>Quakers</hi> peaceably met together, to Wait upon and Worſhip the Living God, according to his Will, in the Way of his Commandments; he, the ſaid <hi>Thornaby,</hi> and other his Agents begun to take the Names of ſome of them ſo met, but not coming to his Purpoſe, in reſpect he did not know them all; and thereupon going away he met with one <hi>Thomas Shore,</hi> a moſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Bad Man (who to the Countrie's great Satisfaction was afterwards for his bad Carriage removed by the Juſtice of <hi>Charles</hi> (then Lord St. <hi>John)</hi> now Marqueſs of <hi>Wincheſter)</hi> who gave him Information of the Names of ſeveral ſo met, which he had not before got; upon which Information, together with what he had got before, he, the ſaid <hi>Thornaby,</hi> together with the ſaid <hi>Henry
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98568:13"/>
Spence,</hi> went to before the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe,</hi> and deſperately Swore againſt a great Number of Perſons, (many whereof he knew not) <hi>That they were at an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nlawful Aſſembly or Conventicle, at the place aforeſaid</hi> (though ſuch as meet to wait upon the Lord, have not heretofore been accounted an Unlawful Aſſembly, but Encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, <hi>Heb.</hi> 10. 25.) and particularly againſt one <hi>Thomas Winn</hi> of <hi>Griſedale,</hi> and <hi>Thomas Bedam</hi>'s Wife of <hi>Hawes,</hi> neither of whom the ſaid <hi>Thornaby</hi> or <hi>Spence</hi> ſaw there; for the ſaid <hi>Thomas Winn</hi> was not that day in <hi>Wenſleydale,</hi> as might have been proved. And for a further Evidence of this mans Wickedneſs, he the ſaid <hi>Thornaby</hi> coming into an Aſſembly afterwards, where many of the ſaid Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple he ſo Swore againſt was preſent, he voluntarily Swore, <hi>He knew not a Face among them but Three,</hi> viz. Richard Robinſon, Bartho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomew Harryſon <hi>and</hi> John Thompſon. And yet upon theſe mens Oathes and Informations, together with the Oathes and Informati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of others, after given, and without calling the Parties accuſed before him, did the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> iſſue forth his Warrants, by which theſe Goods and Chattels here-after-named were taken from the People following in <hi>Wenſleydale.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And <hi>Firſt, James Metcalfe</hi> of <hi>Bainbrigg</hi> and <hi>Anthony Swinbanke</hi> of <hi>Moſedale,</hi> both Conſtables for <hi>Bainbrigg</hi> aforeſaid, with others, upon the 7th day of the 4th Moneth, 1670. by the Warrant or Warrants aforeſaid, did take from <hi>Oſwald Routh</hi> of <hi>Hawes</hi> aforeſaid Three Kine, and the next day one Mare. And the 5th day of the 8th Moneth, 1670. the ſaid Conſtables or their Agents, took from him Braſs and Pewter, altogether worth about 12 l. 2 s.</p>
               <p>The ſame Conſtables, with others, upon the 4th day of the 4th Moneth, 1670. did take from <hi>Richard Routh</hi> of <hi>Hawes</hi> aforeſaid, Braſs and Pewter; and the 8th of the ſame Moneth Five Kine, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together worth 16 l.</p>
               <p>The 7th day of the ſame Moneth, 1670. did the ſame Conſtables take from <hi>Chriſtopher Routh</hi> of <hi>Hawes</hi> aforeſaid (now Priſoner) One Cow, worth about 2 l. 6 s. 8 d.</p>
               <p>And the 8th day of the ſame Moneth did the ſame Conſtables take from <hi>Richard Binkes</hi> of the ſame place One Mare and a Colt of about one year old, which was ſold for 3 l. 18 s. 6 s.</p>
               <p>The ſame day the ſame Perſons took from <hi>Thomas Reedham</hi> of the ſame place one Cow, worth about 2 l. 10 s.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:98568:13"/>
They, or ſome, or one of them, alſo about the ſame time, took from <hi>Fancis Metcalfe</hi> of <hi>Moſedale</hi> in <hi>Wenſleydale</hi> aforeſaid one Cow, worth about 2 l.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All, or moſt of which Goods ſo diſtrained and taken as aforeſaid by Warrant from the ſaid</hi> James Metcalfe, <hi>was either by Relations or Neigbours to the Sufferers bought of the Diſtrainers, though many of them at prety dear Rates, on purpoſe to ſave ſomething for the Sufferers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> Conſtable and <hi>John Metcalfe</hi> Church-Warden (ſo called) both of <hi>Bainbrigg,</hi> and <hi>Francis Lambert</hi> of <hi>Marſett,</hi> Overſeer, together with <hi>William Thornaby</hi> Elder, and <hi>Henry Spence,</hi> Informers; about the ſame time did take from <hi>John Thompſon</hi> of <hi>Blean,</hi> Braſs and Pewter, which they ſold for 1 l. 5 s.</p>
               <p>And from <hi>Bart. Harryſon</hi> of <hi>Counterſett</hi> in <hi>Wenſleydale,</hi> Pewter worth by Eſtimation 4 s.</p>
               <p>From <hi>Michael Pratt</hi> of <hi>Burgehill</hi> in the ſame <hi>Dale,</hi> Pewter worth, by Eſtimation about 15 s.</p>
               <p>The ſame Officers and Informers did alſo come into the Houſe of <hi>Richard Robinſon</hi> of <hi>Counterſett</hi> at the ſame time, and ſome of the Officers often after, but never made any Diſtreſs.</p>
               <p>By Warrant from <hi>Joſeph Cradock</hi> were theſe Goods following in and near <hi>Maſſam</hi> diſtrained, upon the Information of the ſaid <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam Thornaby</hi> the Elder, his Son, and other his Agents, or ſome of them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jane Bridgewater</hi> a poor Widow-Woman, for having a Meeting at her Houſe in <hi>Maſſam</hi> had all ſhe had diſtrained, but to what Value is Uncertain.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Bridgewater</hi> of the ſame place had Goods diſtrained worth by Eſtimation about 2 l.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robert Lodge</hi> of the ſame place, for a Fine of 1 l. 10 s. had Houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold Goods diſtrained worth by Eſtimation about 5 l.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anne Blackburne</hi> of <hi>High-Ellington,</hi> another poor Widow, had Houſhold Goods diſtrained, worth about 3 l. 10 s.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Whitton</hi> of <hi>Pattrick-Brunton</hi> had two Kine taken from him, worth about 5 l.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:98568:14"/>
                  <hi>Marmaduke Beckwith</hi> of <hi>Aldburgh,</hi> had Houſhold Goods diſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but not taken away, for his Brother bought them, and let him have the Uſe of them, worth about 20 l.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>William Beckwith</hi> had Houſhold Goods diſtrained worth 3 l. 10 s.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Pratt,</hi> for a Fine of 10 s. laid on him, had Goods di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained and ſold, worth about 2 l.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Much alſo of the Goods afore-mentioned was bought by Neighbours and Relations to the Sufferers; not out of Envy to the Owners, but out of Pity and good Will to their Harmleſs Neigbours and Friends, on purpoſe to ſave ſomething, if poſſible, out of their Ruins, having, many of them, their Hearts Sadded to ſee ſuch Havock made.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Taken in <hi>Coverdale</hi> upon the account aforeſaid, the 10th day of the 7th Moneth, called <hi>September,</hi> in the Year 1670. <hi>Anthony Slay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> and <hi>Rich. Rinder</hi> Conſtables, by Warrant from the Lord St. <hi>John,</hi> diſtrained and took from <hi>Stephen Winn</hi> of <hi>Melmerby</hi> in <hi>Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale</hi> (now Priſoner) a piece of Cloth, worth about 13 s.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rich. Beck,</hi> Conſtable of <hi>Melmerby</hi> aforeſaid, by Warrant from <hi>Joſeph Craddock</hi> diſtrained and took from the ſaid <hi>Stephen Winn</hi> two Kine and Houſhold Goods, ſo that he neither left Diſh, Dubler, Spoon nor Stool to ſit upon; he alſo diſtrained and ſold two pair of Looms, and other working Inſtruments, and Yarn, he being a Weaver, and Stuff upon the Beam, an unwrought part of it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to others, for whom he wrought it, valued together about 7 l. 10 s. 6 d.</p>
               <p>The 16th day of the Moneth and Year aforeſaid, and by the ſame Warrant, as was ſuppoſed, did <hi>Simon Winn</hi> Conſtable, diſtrain and take from <hi>Richard Geldart</hi> of <hi>Carleton</hi> in <hi>Coverdale</hi> aforeſaid, five Kine and two Heiffers, well worth 13 l.</p>
               <p>And the 25th of the ſame Moneth and Year, and by the ſaid War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of <hi>Lord St. John</hi> did the ſaid Conſtables diſtrain and take from <hi>William Hornor</hi> of <hi>Woodall</hi> in <hi>Coverdale</hi> aforeſaid, ſeven Kine, one Mare, Houſhold Stuff, two Stacks of Hay, and other two parcels of Hay, altogether worth about 26 l.</p>
               <p>And the ſame Conſtables alſo diſtrained from <hi>James Janſon</hi> of the ſame place, Houſhold Goods worth about 5 l.</p>
               <p>But moſt of the Goods afore-mentioned, which were taken by force of the <hi>Lord St. John</hi>'s Warrant, and by the Conſtable who
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98568:14"/>
diſtrained them by virtue of the ſaid Warrant, ſold to ſuch as would buy them, but becauſe not ſold at dear Rates, were either by War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from <hi>Ioſeph Craddock</hi> diſtrained again, or otherwiſe by his means and cruelty forced to be compounded, bought and contracted for again, under pretence of a Combination to defeat the King, thereby afrighting the poor Innocent People, who had bought them out of their Bargains, to the ſubverſion of Commerce and Dealing in this behalf, they knowing no Law to prohibit the Buyer from peaceably enjoying, and otherwiſe diſpoſing of what he had ſo bought from thoſe authorized to ſell, as the Conſtables, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in this Caſe of force by the ſaid Act and Warrants thereon grounded was ſaid to be, neither any Law which binds the Conſtables to ſell at dearer Rates than they can get: And it was alſo contrary to the Order of his Son <hi>Thomas Craddock</hi> at the <hi>Quarter-Seſſions</hi> for the Town of <hi>Richmond</hi> to the Conſtable there, who affirming, <hi>That he could not get the Goods he had ſo taken in diſtreſs ſold,</hi> or to that pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, (as is remembred) told him, <hi>He muſt ſell them, though he ſold Ten Pounds worth for Ten Shillings.</hi> And here all may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive their Evil-will to the Sufferers, and thoſe that wiſhed them Well; for if they could but perceive what moſt tended to their Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>advantage, they would chuſe that which moſt conduced to their Ruin; for rather than they ſhould forbear diſtraining, becauſe they, to wit, the Conſtables, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> could not get the Goods ſold, few or none having a mind to buy ſuch Ill-gotten Goods, they muſt have liberty to ſell, though in a manner for nothing: But if any that bought them were judged to bear good Will to the Sufferers, they might be troubled, under pretence of <hi>Defeating the King,</hi> as thoſe poor Buyers and Conſtable were, who all or ſome of them were had to the <hi>Seſſions,</hi> and there threatned, and the Conſtable impriſoned and fined 20 l. as is remembred. And herein, as well as in other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, the Malice of ſome men was made manifeſt; and that it was they in this ſence that ſought Life more than the <hi>Quakers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Upon the 2d day of the 2d Moneth called <hi>April,</hi> in the Year 1671. came one <hi>Richard Murrow,</hi> then of <hi>Burton</hi> in or near <hi>Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale,</hi> Conſtable, now deceaſed, together with <hi>William Thornaby</hi> the Younger, of <hi>Richmond,</hi> (Son to the aforeſaid <hi>William Thornaby</hi> the Elder) Informer, into the Aſſembly of the Lords People at the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:98568:15"/>
Houſe of <hi>Thomas Simpſon</hi> in <hi>Burton</hi> aforeſaid, where they were met in the fear of the Lord, and to wait upon him; and coming in, the ſaid Conſtable ſeeing them met, in a Scornful manner ſaid, <hi>They are pannelled;</hi> and when they had according to their former uſe ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the Names of thoſe ſo met, the Conſtable ſaid, <hi>He had a War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant to ſearch and rifle among them;</hi> which ſome deſiring to ſee, he refuſed, only pull'd out ſome Papers, but what was in them they did not know; and being adviſed, <hi>To take heed what he did, leſt he run himſelf into a Snare,</hi> he refuſed to hear; and having ſearched the Houſe, and not coming to his purpoſe, they went to the Stable, wherein were three Mares, one of the mans own who own'd the Stable, and two of his Friends, which they had borrowed, but the Door being bolted, and they not getting in, the ſaid Conſtable returned and told the Owner of the Houſe, <hi>He muſt open the Door;</hi> which not being done accordingly, but he adviſed, <hi>To take heed what he did;</hi> He Scoffingly refuſed the Advice, and ſaid, <hi>He would have it opened, or he would break it;</hi> and further ſaid, <hi>He would Charge others to do it for him;</hi> which he did, but they refuſed; at which he was grieved, and ſaid, <hi>They had as good have held a Cow to the Bull, if he lived:</hi> By which may be ſeen his Forwardneſs, Envy and Malice, whom God did not ſuffer long to eſcape: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Thornaby</hi> the Informer ſaid, <hi>Charge me, and I will do it,</hi> or to that purpoſe; but the other being as willing as he, they both went, and having got into the Houſe took thence one Mare, which <hi>William Hornor</hi> had borrowed, with a Saddle and Woman's-Seat thereon, worth altogether about 2 l. And another which <hi>Stephen Winn</hi> had borrowed, with a Saddle and Woman's-Seat thereon, worth about 4 l. 10 s. And a little Mare belonging to the Owner of the Houſe; all which they carried away to the Conſtable's Houſe; but a little Girle pluck't off the Halter from the little Mare's Head, whereby ſhe got away; which when the Conſtable perceived, he was grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and came again to the Stable, and ſaid, <hi>They had loſt one of their Prizes; but ſhe muſt be made good.</hi> Afterwards the ſame day by the Permiſſion or other Aſſent or Agreement of the ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, the ſaid young <hi>Thornaby,</hi> the Informer, carried away the remaining two Mares towards <hi>Richmond,</hi> whither the next day, being the 3d day of the Moneth aforeſaid, followed the ſaid Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, and came to the Houſe of old <hi>William Thornaby</hi> to lodge,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98568:15"/>
where the next Morning he got his Breakfaſt prety well, and was Curſing of the <hi>Quakers</hi> (ſo called) in the preſence of one <hi>Thomas Winn,</hi> who gave the Relation of it; but going from thence to the Carriers Houſe in that Town, about the ſending of a Daughter of his to <hi>London,</hi> where he did alſo eat and drink, he ſuddainly fell down dead, over, upon or beſides the Table, where he had been eating, and was about to count Money, and part of the Money fell from him. A True Evidence of God's Righteous Judgments upon him, who had ſo Audaciouſly behaved himſelf againſt his innocent Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, and may give ſufficient Warning and Caution to ſuch Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers and Conſtables in this day, and forever hereafter, as do not in a Moderate Fear abſtain from ſuch Actions as this man purſued, whoſe Intentions were Wicked; for when ſome of his Neighbours, (which were no <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſo called) asked him, <hi>What made him ſo Sawſie;</hi> he ſaid, <hi>He had not been ſo Sawſie, but he would be;</hi> and ſometimes ſaid, <hi>They</hi> (to wit, the Informers, Conſtables, and the reſt) <hi>would not leave them</hi> (to wit, the <hi>Quakers) all a Groat;</hi> and <hi>That they would take a Courſe with them,</hi> and ſuch like Wicked Stuff, which were too long to relate; by which may be ſeen his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy and Wicked Intentions; but God cutting him off in the midſt of his Iniquity, before he had accompliſhed what in Evil Intent he aimed at, may ſignifie to all them that remain and imploy themſelves in ſuch Wicked Actions, and Spoiling of their Neighbours Goods (as this man did) who proffered to ſeek them in the Night-ſeaſon; that it is not the Cloathing themſelves with the <hi>King's Authority</hi> &amp; <hi>Warrants,</hi> and ſaying, <hi>They have the King's Authority &amp; Iuſtices Warrants; and that they muſt and will Obey; that will excuſe and deliver in the Day when God comes to plead with men;</hi> for if that could have been an Excuſe and brought Deliverance, then the moſt Mighty men that were in the Army of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> might have been excuſed, who had the King's Command, and that a Mighty King too, for the binding and caſting of <hi>Shadrach, Meſhack</hi> and <hi>Abednego</hi> into the fiery Furnace, and have pleaded, <hi>They could not help it; they were Compelled to it</hi> (as ſome in theſe dayes have ſaid) But this Command, though from a Mighty King, as aforeſaid, excuſed not the matter ſo, but that they ſuffered Death by Force of that Flame, which was appointed for the Deſtruction of others: Which Thing is Worthy to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken notice of by all the Officers and Conſtables in <hi>England</hi> at
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98568:16"/>
this day, to whom it hath been often in my Heart, <hi>It is a Figure;</hi> and therefore had need to be warned and adviſed by the ſame, that the Command they purſue be Righteous; and alſo, that what they do, be done in the fear of the Lord; for the Lord knows how to deliver the Righteous, as he did <hi>Shadrach, Meſhack</hi> and <hi>Abednego,</hi> who could not bow to the King's Will in that day, no more than the Innocent People called <hi>Quakers</hi> can bow to the Wills of them that would limit the holy One of <hi>Iſrael</hi> at this day; and the ſame God alſo knows how to reſerve the Wicked, as he did this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtable, unto the day of Judgment, to be Puniſhed, which we do not rejoyce over, as Glorying in any man Deſtruction, but only ſet forth to the end, that others may ſee and be warned, leſt they likewiſe come into the like Condemnation. It is alſo worthy to be further taken notice of, That old <hi>William Thornaby</hi>'s Wife and young <hi>William Thornaby</hi>'s Mother, who was hardned in the Sin of her Husband and Son, having been viſited with Sickneſs much of the time of their afore-mentioned Wicked Imployment, dyed the ſame day, and as was reported, about the very ſame Hour her Son was exerciſed in taking the Mares aforeſaid: and the two Mares them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſo taken as aforeſaid, alſo ſhortly after dyed in the Poſſeſſion of the ſaid <hi>Thornabyes,</hi> or the one of them, as others ſo got before by them likewiſe did; and there was neither <hi>King</hi> nor <hi>Poor</hi> got any part out of them, but <hi>Thornabyes</hi> went with the whole, which both the ſaid <hi>Joſeph Craddock</hi> and <hi>James Metcalfe,</hi> notwithſtanding their pretended zeal for the King, could diſpence withal.</p>
               <p>Alſo the Goods of one <hi>James Calvert</hi> of <hi>Burton,</hi> in or near <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhopdale,</hi> together with the Goods of a Friend there, called <hi>Jere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah Simpſon,</hi> were diſtrained to a great value, by Warrants (as was ſaid) from <hi>Joſeph Craddock</hi> (for we were ſometimes forced to take their Words, they being unwilling, and ſometimes reſuſing to ſhew their Warrants) for the Offence (as it was called) of the afore-named <hi>Stephen Winn,</hi> who being at <hi>Prayer</hi> in the Houſe of the afore-named <hi>Thomas Simpſon</hi> in <hi>Burton</hi> aforeſaid, where the Por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons diſtrained on were preſent; and the above-named <hi>Thornaby</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in, and finding the ſaid <hi>Stephen</hi> at Prayer, as aforeſaid, after ſome ſeemingly wondering Expreſſions, he went away and Inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the ſaid <hi>Joſeph Craddock;</hi> but whether his Information upon Oath was, <hi>That he was Praying only, or that he was Preaching and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:98568:16"/>
Teaching,</hi> we know not, having never ſeen the Information, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may be, would he greatly ſcruple what he Swore, as may be perceived by his former deportment; but whatſoever he Swore, it was <hi>Prayer only</hi> that the ſaid <hi>Stephen</hi> at that time was exerciſed in, and for which Offence it was ſaid, the Goods were diſtrained; by which it may be perceived, that neither <hi>Law</hi> nor <hi>Scripture</hi> was any Limit to theſe men in their Proceedings; for the Apoſtle ſaith, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. &amp; 8. <hi>I will therefore, that men Pray every where, lifting up holy Hands, without Wrath or Doubting.</hi> And the very Law by which they did pretend to proceed impoſeth no Penalty upon any for the meer Act of Prayer; and if it did, yet it were contrary to the Apoſtles Doctrine, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 17. who commands <hi>To Pray without ceaſing,</hi> and alſo to Chriſt's, <hi>Luke</hi> 18. 1. and contrary to Law alſo, as appears by <hi>Shepheard</hi> in his <hi>Grand Abridgment,</hi> part 3. pag. 9, &amp; 274. <hi>Nay, though a Statute ſhould be made to prohibit men to Pray to God, yet the ſame were void,</hi> as appears by the places afore-cited, and thoſe quoted by him: Read alſo the Epiſtle to the <hi>Engliſh Tranſlation of the Mirrour of Iuſtice.</hi> And as if this were not Wickedneſs enough, they impoſed the Puniſhment of that which they call the Fault of one upon another, contrary to the Scripture, which they have ſometimes (though falſly) called their <hi>Rule,</hi> which ſaith, <hi>It ſhall no more be ſaid, the Fathers have eaten a ſowr Grape, and the Childrens Teeth are ſet on Edge; for every man ſhall dye for his own Iniquity; and the Soul that Sins ſhall dye,</hi> not another; and it is alſo a Rule in their own Law, <hi>Nemo pro Alieno delicto Punitur:</hi> But they neither regarded Scripture nor the Law, further than they will ſuit their Envy and Covetous Ends. For ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſometimes (but falſly) condemned the <hi>Quakers,</hi> ſo by them called, for <hi>Denying Prayer;</hi> they in this caſe Condemn, and go about to Puniſh for Praying; and ſo are all found in the Confuſion, Lyes and Falſhoods.</p>
               <p>The Conſtable of <hi>Bellerby,</hi> with others, about the times above<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, or ſome of them, did diſtrain and take from <hi>Ralph Aineſly</hi> of the ſame place, by Warrant from the Lord <hi>St. John,</hi> Pewter worth about 16 s. and after that, by Warrant from <hi>Joſeph Craddock,</hi> two Kine, one Mare, two Stacks of Hay, and a Burden of Hay off his Wife's Head, together with three Burden Ropes and two
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:98568:17"/>
Hay-Spades (by which it appears they will leave little) altogether worth at leaſt 16 l. 10 s.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="history">
               <head>
                  <hi>More taken in</hi> Swaledale.</head>
               <p>Upon the 21th day of the 12th moneth, called <hi>February,</hi> in the year 1670. came <hi>Henry Watſon</hi> Conſtable, <hi>Henry Thwaite</hi> of <hi>Reeth</hi> in <hi>Swaledale</hi> Overſeer, <hi>William Thornaby</hi> the Elder, <hi>William Thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naby</hi> the Younger and one <hi>John Alliſon</hi> Informers, to the aforeſaid Houſe of <hi>Elizabeth Cherry</hi> Widow in <hi>Swaledale,</hi> and under Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of the Lord <hi>St. John</hi>'s Warrant, and to ſeek for a Meeting, they broke the Door of the ſaid Houſe after they had been infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by one of their own Company which was in the Houſe, <hi>That there was no Meeting there;</hi> and having ſo broken the Door, by another Warrant from <hi>James Metcalfe,</hi> they diſtrained and took out of the Houſe in Bedding, Wearing-Apparel and other things belonging to this poor Widow and her Children, to the value of about 16 l.</p>
               <p>The ſame perſons alſo (ſave <hi>Henry Watſon)</hi> the ſame day, by Warrant from the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe,</hi> did diſtrain of <hi>Jeoffrey Loneſdale</hi> of <hi>Healy</hi> in <hi>Swaledale,</hi> Stockings, Wearing Apparel, Bedding, and other things, worth by eſtimation 20 l.</p>
               <p>The 1ſt day of the 1ſt moneth (called <hi>March)</hi> following, did the ſame <hi>Henry Watſon, Henry Thwaite</hi> and one <hi>Mark Hutchinſon,</hi> by Warrant from the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe,</hi> diſtrain of <hi>Ralph Pea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cock</hi> of <hi>Winterings</hi> in <hi>Swaledale,</hi> ſix Beaſts, worth about 14 l.</p>
               <p>Which with ſome of the other there taken aforeſaid, they ſold to ſuch as would buy them, but at what Rates hath not as yet been to the Compiler hereof known.</p>
               <p>Upon or about the 19th day of the 12th moneth (called <hi>Februa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry)</hi> 1670. came <hi>William Thornaby</hi> the younger and <hi>Iohn Alliſon,</hi> both of <hi>Richmond,</hi> Informers, together with the above-named <hi>Henry Thwaite</hi> Overſeer, to the Houſe of the ſaid <hi>Elizabeth Cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,</hi> under pretence to ſearch for a Conventicle, where finding none beſides thoſe of the Family, ſave <hi>Ia. Longſtaff</hi> and the ſaid Widow <hi>Cherry</hi>'s Siſter, and <hi>Elizabeth Orton,</hi> who was there viſiting the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:98568:17"/>
ſaid Widow <hi>Cherry</hi>'s Daughter, then very Weak, and not likely to live, which <hi>Thornaby</hi> perceiving would have gone into the inner Rooms, under pretence to ſee if there were no more there; and ſaid, He had a Warrant from the Lord St. <hi>John,</hi> to break open the Doors; ſhe bid him ſhew it; who pulling it forth began to read it; ſhe ſaid, <hi>He might read what he would, for ſhe could not read,</hi> but ſaid, <hi>William Orton was a little off intending to go home, we ſhall call him in to read it;</hi> which being done, and <hi>William</hi> being come into the Houſe to read it, told them (having read it) that that Warrant did not concern that place nor any other, except there were an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawful Aſſembly; nevertheleſs Widdow <hi>Cherry</hi> opened the Doors for their ſatisfaction, who ſearching found no more: only <hi>Katherine Longſtaff</hi> who came to ſee her ſick Kinſwoman, and <hi>Edward Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamſon</hi> came into the Houſe while they were ſearching, which when <hi>Thornaby</hi> perceived he began to ſet down their Names, but <hi>Kathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rine Longſtaff</hi> refuſed to tell hers, being, as ſhe ſignified to them, one that frequented their Pariſh Church, and came but to ſee her Kinſwoman, whereupon the ſaid <hi>Thornaby</hi> and <hi>Alliſon</hi> went to the aforeſaid <hi>James Metcalfe,</hi> who as one fit for their deſign, anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed their Ends, and granted forth a Warrant againſt <hi>William Orton</hi> and his Daughter, not knowing either her Name or Age, and fined them together 10 s. <hi>Katherine Longſtaff</hi> 5 s. <hi>James Longſtaff</hi> 5 s. and <hi>Edward Williamſon</hi> 5 s. and further alſo fined <hi>William Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> for the Houſe 9 l. and <hi>James Longſtaff</hi> 5 l. and Widow <hi>Cher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> the reſt. Whereupon <hi>William Orton, Katherine Longſtaff,</hi> the Conſtable, and ſome other Neighbours went to the ſaid <hi>James Met<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calfe,</hi> and told him of the Informers unjuſt Swearing againſt them, and <hi>Katherine Longſtaff</hi> alſo carryed a Certificate under the Prieſt of the Pariſh his Hand, ſignifying that ſhe was no <hi>Quaker</hi> (ſo called) but frequented their Church, and another, that ſhe had received the Lords Supper (as they called it) nevertheleſs the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> would not recall his Warrant, whereupon <hi>William Orton</hi> put in his Appeal, and the next general Quarter Seſſions held at <hi>Thrusk</hi> had a Tryal with the Informer, where the Records of the pretended Conviction being read, there proved but five Perſons in it, whereof Widdow <hi>Cherry</hi> Owner of the Houſe was one, which not being according to Law muſt needs be void, the Act by which they pretended to proceed, requiring that there be five Perſons
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:98568:18"/>
beſides thoſe of the Family: Whereupon the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> (being ſtill willing to aſſiſt the ſaid Informers in their Unjuſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings) would not acknowledge that the ſaid <hi>William Orton</hi> did Appeal from him, though himſelf at the ſame Seſſions had delivered the ſame Appeal, together with the pretended Record of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction into the Court, whereupon (to his ſhame) <hi>William Orton</hi> did prove in open Court, that he did appeal from him, and that he drew the Appeal in <hi>James Metcalfes</hi> own Houſe, by his Inſtructions, and by a preſident the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> gave him to draw it by; Alſo the ſaid <hi>William Ortons</hi> Counſel urged that there ought to be Witneſſes beſides the Informers; but the ſaid <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing willing ſtill to carry on the Informers unjuſt deſigns (though all the Bench was againſt it, ſeeing their Illegal Proceedings) ſaid, <hi>That Old</hi> William Thornaby <hi>was Informer, and Young</hi> William Thornaby <hi>and</hi> Alliſon <hi>were Witneſſes;</hi> which was not Truth; for Old <hi>William Thornaby</hi> was not at Widow <hi>Cherry</hi>'s Houſe that day, neither had <hi>Iames Metcalfe</hi> any Information from him touching that matter.</p>
               <p>Whereupon the Juſtices ordered, <hi>That</hi> William Orton <hi>ſhould have his Money upon his Appeal again; and that the Conviction was Illegal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs by what is here expreſſed may eaſily be perceived how the ſaid <hi>Iames Metcalfe</hi> endeavoured himſelf (though often to his ſhame) to vindicate and carry on the Intereſt of thoſe <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>njuſt In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers</hi> and <hi>Falſe Swearers;</hi> for when Truth would not do it, he would ſo far diſhonour himſelf as to tell Lyes on their behalfs, as in this his ſaying, <hi>That Old</hi> William Thornaby <hi>was Informer;</hi> who neither was there, nor ſaw the matter done, neither gave Evidence nor Information of it; and alſo refuſed to acknowledge the Appeal, which he himſelf had been aſſiſtent in drawing, as aboveſaid. And in all things demeaned himſelf as one that delighted to make himſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned in carrying on the Informers Intereſt, or otherwiſe deſirous to do his Neighbour a Miſchief.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="history">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:98568:18"/>
               <head>Sufferings in and about <hi>Richmond</hi> on the ſame Account.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Jane Chayter</hi> Widow, and <hi>John Chayter</hi> her Son, both of <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> upon the Information of the aforeſaid <hi>William Thornaby</hi> was by <hi>John Bartlet</hi> Mayor, fined 30 l. for having a Meeting in their Houſe the 13th of the 3d Moneth, 1670. and though the ſaid Mayor, when he came in found none but his Harmleſs Neighbours waiting upon the Lord in Silence, yet by Warrants from him did <hi>Mich. Fawcett</hi> and <hi>Richard Hogg,</hi> Conſtables, with others, take Stuff and other Goods, ſo that the Damage did amount to the Sum of 20 l.</p>
               <p>About the 10th day of the 7th Moneth, in the Year 1670. the ſaid <hi>John Chaytor</hi> upon the account of meeting with the People of God in Scorn called <hi>Quakers,</hi> was fined 2 l. and had Goods taken out of his Shop for the ſame, by Warrant from the ſaid Mayor and Recorder, by the aforeſaid Conſtable and others, worth about 3 l.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Johnſon</hi> of the ſame place, about the ſame time fined 1 l. 10 s. had Goods taken out of his Houſe by the ſaid Conſtables, upon Warrant from the aforeſaid Mayor and Recorder, worth about 1 l. 15 s.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mary Adamſon</hi> of <hi>Richmond,</hi> about the ſame time fined 10 s. had Goods taken out of her Houſe worth about 14 s.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iſabel Williamſon,</hi> a poor Woman of the ſame place, who had little but her Hand-labour to relieve her ſelf with, was by the parties aforeſaid fined 5 s. and had by the ſaid Conſtables her Wear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-Apparel diſtrained, worth about 1 l.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Robert Cutter</hi> of <hi>Ravenſworth</hi> near <hi>Richmond,</hi> for being at a Mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting at the Houſe of the ſaid Widow <hi>Chaytor,</hi> about the 15th day of the 3d Moneth 1670. was fined 5 s. for which Corn was taken from him, by Warrant from one <hi>William Robinſon,</hi> worth about 13 s.</p>
               <p>The ſame <hi>Robert Cutter</hi> about the 10th day of the 7th Moneth, 1670. was fined 2 l. for which he had Corn taken from him, by Warrant from the aforeſaid <hi>William Robinſon,</hi> worth about 2 l.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:98568:19"/>
About the 26th day of the 8th Moneth, 1670. the ſaid <hi>John Chay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor</hi> was fined 2 l. 5 s. for which, by Warrant from the aforeſaid Mayor and Recorder, the ſaid Conſtables did take Goods out of his Shop, worth about 3 l. 5 s.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thomas Iohnſon</hi> the ſame time fined 2 l. 10 s. had Goods taken by the ſaid Conſtables upon like Warrant, worth about 3 l. 10 s.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn Hopps</hi> of <hi>Richmond</hi> fined alſo 1 l. 5 s. had Goods taken out of his Shop, by the ſame or like Warrant, worth about 1 l. 15 s.</p>
               <p>And at another time for a Fine of 10 s. had Goods taken out of his Shop, by Warrant from the aforeſaid Recorder, worth about 1 l. 4 s.</p>
               <p>The aforeſaid <hi>Thomas Iohnſon</hi> about the ſame time, by the ſame Warrant and Officers, and for the like Fine of 10 s. had Houſhold Goods taken from him, worth about 14 s.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Mary Adamſon</hi> aforeſaid fined 1 l. 10 s. had Houſhold-Goods taken out of her Houſe, worth about 2 l.</p>
               <p>Alſo, <hi>Iane Chaytor,</hi> Mother of the ſaid <hi>Iohn Chaytor,</hi> for meeting with the aforeſaid People was fined 2 l. 10 s. for which Goods was taken out of the Shop of the ſaid <hi>Iohn Chaytor,</hi> worth to the value of 3 l. 5 s.</p>
               <p>The aforeſaid <hi>Iohn Chaytor,</hi> for having a Meeting at his Houſe the 12th day of the 12th Moneth called <hi>February,</hi> in the Year 1670. was fined by <hi>Thomas Craddock</hi> Recorder for <hi>Richmond,</hi> aforeſaid, upon the Information of the aforeſaid <hi>W. Thornaby,</hi> the Sum of 20 l. for which he had Shop-Goods diſtrained and taken from him upon the 21ſt &amp; 22d dayes of the 2d Moneth, in the Year 1671. by <hi>Henry Shaw, Iames Sayer</hi> and others, by Warrant from the ſaid <hi>Thomas Craddock,</hi> worth about 33 l.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The ſaid</hi> John <hi>Appealing, had his Tryal at the next</hi> Quarter-Seſſions <hi>held for the ſaid Burrough of</hi> Richmond, <hi>where the</hi> Jury <hi>found for the ſaid</hi> John Chaytor, <hi>and againſt the Informers; ſo that up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their Verdict, the ſaid</hi> John <hi>ſhould have had all his ſaid Goods (ſo diſtrained as aforeſaid) again: But one of the ſaid Conſtables (to wit,</hi> Henry Shaw) <hi>having within the time limited by the ſaid</hi> Act <hi>for Appeal, ſold the Goods amounting to the value of 33 l to the Informer</hi> Thornaby, <hi>as was ſaid for 20 l. the ſaid</hi> Thornaby <hi>and</hi> Shaw <hi>pretending, that the ſaid Goods ſo ſold was diſpoſed of that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:98568:19"/>
they could not be had again. All <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> the ſaid</hi> John Chaytor <hi>had or could get without Suit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which he was not willing to make uſe of; notwithſtanding their bad dealing with him, was only 20 l. the pretended Price the Goods were ſold for: So that his Loſs in this particular, beſides Charges of the Appeal, amount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Sum of 13 l.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo the ſaid <hi>Iohn Chaytor</hi> for having a Meeting in his Houſe on the 25th day of the 4th Moneth called <hi>June,</hi> 1671. was fined 20 l. for which by Warrant from the ſaid <hi>Thomas Craddock,</hi> he had Shop Goods to wit, a certain Commodity called <hi>Battery)</hi> diſtrained and taken from him by <hi>Henry Shaw, Robert Burton</hi> and <hi>James Sayer,</hi> Conſtables, to the value of about 20 l. 16 s. which Goods being delivered to <hi>Richard Dawſon,</hi> then Mayor of the ſaid Town of <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond,</hi> he kept to his own Uſe, and as is ſuppoſed, paid down the 20 l. they were diſtrained for, at the next Seſſions held for the ſaid Town: But his Wife <hi>Iſabell Dawſon</hi> being troubled at ſuch Unjuſt Dealings and Proceedings againſt an Innocent People, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of their Conſciences, would not have had her Husband to have dealt ſo by them, or in that kind concerned himſelf with them (as I think I have heard) but he not regarding her, or not ſubmitting to that wholeſome Advice, given by her unto him, did continue the ſaid Goods in his own Poſſeſſion, with intent (as it ſhould ſeem) to convert the ſame to his own uſe. But ſome time after being out of his Mayorality, he dyed, and his Eſtate thereupon coming to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided between his Children and Widow, ſhe the ſaid <hi>Iſabell,</hi> then his Widow, deſired, that the ſame parcel of Goods ſo taken from the ſaid <hi>John Chaytor</hi> (if it were poſſible) might be made parcel of her ſhare of her ſaid deceaſed Husband's Goods, which thing did accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly fall out; and being in her own Poſſeſſion, or at her Diſpoſe, ſhe did enquire of the ſaid <hi>Iohn Chaytor,</hi> the Value and Quantity or Weight of the ſaid Goods, ſo taken from him; which when ſhe underſtood, <hi>ſhe did Fully reſtore unto him in Weight, Worth, or other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the Whole Value or Quantity of the ſaid Goods:</hi> Which thing we do not here make mention of, and Report as being a Suffering, or an Act whereby the ſaid <hi>Iohn Chaytor</hi> did come to any Loſs, for that was made up and Re-pay'd by her in manner as aforeſaid; but this we make mention of and Record to the intent, that ſo Noble an Act of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:98568:20"/>
this Woman, ſo truly worthy and deſerving Commendations in this behalf, might not be hid in obſcurity, but that the ſame might be publiſhed, to the intent, that how far ſoever this Teſtimony of the hard Uſage of the Lords People, by the hands of Unreaſonable and Wicked men may go, this good Deed of this Woman, ſo truly wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, as aforeſaid, may in this behalf be alſo born Teſtimony of; that ſo no one Perſon herein concerned may want of that due Weight and Meaſure that of Right belongs to them; but that as the Wicked and Unreaſonable meet with the Report of their Wickedneſs and Unreaſonableneſs to their Shame, ſo the Good Deeds and Upright Dealings of the Honeſt and Truly Conſcientious, may alſo commend them to their Praiſe, knowing, and being further perſwaded, that as this Woman, or any other comes to be led and guided by that Principle of Truth and Righteouſneſs in their Inward Parts, that led and guided her at this time, to the doing of this Worthy and truly Commendable Act, the ſame Principle will never leave them, as they are guided by it, until it hath led them unto the Light of Life, and brought them unto the Banqueting-houſe of the Lords Love, and to that which is truly Praiſe-worthy before him; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing diſobeyed and rejected, will become their Condemnation, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding any former notable Act done by them; therefore let every ſuch one mind to keep to the ſame, and whilſt they have a time to prize it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="history">
               <head>More taken in <hi>Burton, Coverdale</hi> and <hi>Wenſley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale</hi> upon the like Account, as followeth.</head>
               <p>Upon the 4th day of the 10th moneth, 1671. <hi>George Ryder</hi> Conſtable of <hi>Burton</hi> aforeſaid, and <hi>Thomas Crookey</hi> Overſeer, by Warrant from <hi>James Metcalfe,</hi> did diſtrain and take from <hi>Thomas Simpſon</hi> of the ſame <hi>Burton,</hi> two Kine and four Sheep, worth 6 l. 10 s.</p>
               <p>The pretended Crime being becauſe ſome Friends met at his Houſe to wait upon the Lord the 17th day of the 9th moneth in the year 1670. which was informed againſt as an Unlawful Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:98568:20"/>
And upon the ſame day the Conſtable did diſtrain and take from <hi>Jeremiah Simpſon</hi> of the ſame <hi>Burton,</hi> and Brother of the ſaid <hi>Thomas Simpſon,</hi> ſeveral Implements of Houſhold-ſtuff to the value of 4 s.</p>
               <p>Upon the 7th day of the 10th moneth, 1671. by the ſame War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant from <hi>James Metcalfe,</hi> came <hi>Iohn Watſon</hi> and <hi>Thomas Stephen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> Conſtables of <hi>Melmerby</hi> in <hi>Coverdale,</hi> and <hi>Iohn Smithies</hi> Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeer, with <hi>William Thornaby</hi> the younger and <hi>Henry Spence</hi> Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, to the Houſe of <hi>Stephen Winn</hi> in <hi>Melmerby</hi> aforeſaid, who was from home, and none in the Houſe but his own Family, except two or three Women that came with their Work to bear <hi>Stephen Winne</hi>'s Wife Company; the Conſtable <hi>Iohn Watſon</hi> ſaid, <hi>He might ſee what Company there was, and he muſt ſee if there were not a Conventicle:</hi> To which <hi>Stephen Winne</hi>'s Wife replyed, <hi>It is not uſual where People come together to worſhip God, to follow their Outward Employments, as you ſee we do</hi> (they being then at Work) or words to that purpoſe; and further told them, <hi>There was no Conventicle:</hi> To which <hi>William Thornaby</hi> the younger ſaid, <hi>There were three</hi> (meaning the three Women that were come in) <hi>and there might be other two within, and then there will be a Conventicle;</hi> and read a Warrant for breaking in, if refuſed to enter where ſuch Meeting is known to be: but this Warrant could not reach then to that Place, becauſe there was then no Meeting known to be there, as indeed there was none at that time, which they likely before<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hand knew well enough. But they having another Deſign, and the Conſtable too willing and ready to comply with the Evil Intent of the Informers went to an inner Door, which being locked they vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently broke open, and broke and ſpoiled ſome things thereby; but finding none, the Conſtable bid to open the next Door, which <hi>Stephen</hi>'s Wife (who perceived their Deſign) refuſed, only told them, <hi>There was none there;</hi> but that would not ſerve, for that Door was broken open alſo, and being broken, then <hi>William Thor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naby</hi> began to pull the Bedding off the Bed, and opened a large Cheſt, and groaped in the Corners of it, and ſought a Box to the bottom in which was ſome Linnen, <hi>more like one that was ſeeking for</hi> MONEY <hi>than a</hi> MEETING: And the ſaid <hi>Thornaby</hi> ſought the Buttery, to ſee what he could find there worth carrying away, and gathered their Wearing Apparel together; and when one that
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:98568:21"/>
ſaw it told him, <hi>He was a right Plunderer;</hi> the ſaid <hi>Thornaby</hi> reply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>It might not be the laſt time he might Plunder there;</hi> though then they took what they well could; for of Bed-Clothes and Yarn they took to the worth of about 4 l. And the ſaid <hi>Stephen Winne</hi> being a poor man, was by this and the like former Cruelties, left in Want of Neceſſaries for his poor Family, not having any manner of Bed-Clothes for him and his ſaid Family to lie on, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the Abuſe his Wife ſometimes ſuſtained from the ſaid Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers, and their Affrighting of his Children by their Boiſterous De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment, who, or one of them this time ſo vehemently cryed, that <hi>Henry Spence</hi> the Informer, a Wicked and Bad Man, deſired them <hi>to get done, he could not endure to hear the Child cry ſo:</hi> and by this Cry, which made even the Wicked and Ungodly relent, it may eaſily be perceived, their Deportment was Wicked and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comely.</p>
               <p>Upon the 5th day of the 11th moneth (called <hi>Ianuary)</hi> 1671. <hi>Anthony Swinbank</hi> of <hi>Moſedale</hi> Conſtable, <hi>Geoffrey D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nſdall</hi> of <hi>Gayle</hi> and <hi>Richard Metcalfe</hi> of <hi>Aporſet,</hi> the one being a Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warden (ſo called) and the other an Overſeer, did by Warrant from the aforeſaid <hi>Iames Metcalfe,</hi> dated (as was ſaid) a year be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, diſtrain and take from the aforeſaid <hi>Chriſtopher Routh</hi> of <hi>Hawes</hi> in <hi>Wenſleydale</hi> five Beaſts, worth about 9 l.</p>
               <p>And we were further informed from a Credible Hand, That the ſaid <hi>Iames Metcalfe</hi> Urged or Threatned the Conſtable to diſtrain, who being unwilling thereunto alledged, <hi>He knew not the Goods,</hi> or to the like purpoſe (as is remembred) then <hi>Iames Metcalfe</hi> told him, <hi>He knew his Neighbour</hi> Francis Metcalfe's <hi>Goods;</hi> to which (as we had notice) the Conſtable replyed, <hi>He</hi> (to wit, <hi>Francis Metcalfe) was grown poor, and had not a Cow but as he hired:</hi> then <hi>Iames Metcalfe</hi> asked, <hi>If they did not bring the Milk into</hi> Francis's <hi>Houſe?</hi> The Conſtable ſaid <hi>Yes: James Metcalfe</hi> replyed, <hi>She might be diſtrained,</hi> or to this purpoſe, as is remembred. Which much manifeſts the continued Wickedneſs of this man (to wit, <hi>James Metcalfe)</hi> he appearing as one that had ſhut out all Pity, and given up himſelf to anſwer the Informers Ends, and made himſelf Inſtrnmental towards the Ruin of his Neighbours, whom God ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered not long to eſcape; for ſhortly after this he dyed, and was
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:98568:21"/>
cut off to the Informers Loſs, who not long after ſled or departed out of theſe Parts, one of his chief Props and Supports being on this wife fallen.</p>
               <p>And there were ſeveral others that had Fines impoſed on them; ſome the Conſtables or other Officers would Labour or endeavour with Kinsfolks, Relations or Neighbours to lay down, and have ſometimes laid it down themſelves, rather than they would levy for the ſame, &amp; ſometimes Neighbours out of kindneſs have driven away and hid the Parties Goods that were to be diſtrained, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Owners Conſent or Knowledge; nay, againſt their Wills, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they would not have ſeen ſuch ſpoil &amp; havock made of the <hi>Goods</hi> of thoſe whom they knew to be Peaceable and Harmleſs People, and Laboured, and do Labour in Honeſt things to be ſerviceable in their Generation. And ſeveral of the ſaid Officers have expreſſed the trouble which was upon them to be concern'd in ſuch things as tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Injury of their Honeſt and Harmleſs Neighbours: By which it is manifeſt, that according to the Interpretation they put upon the ſaid Act, or rather by the Uſe made of it, the Honeſt and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcientious were and are Troubled, Burdened and Oppreſſed; and the Envious, Cruel, Unmerciful and Covetous Strengthened, Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held and Encouraged. Now the hand of the Evil Doer ſhould not be ſtrengthened. And this will be found a Truth, <hi>That to Juſtifie the Wicked, and Condemn the Righteous, are both an Abomination to the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>All which Goods ſo as aforeſaid taken, and Spoil before-mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed made in the Intereſt of Honeſt, Harmleſs, Self-denying People, was for no greater, or other Crime or Offence, ſave only for peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably meeting together, ſimply and Innocently to wait upon and worſhip the One, True and Living God in Spirit and Truth, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his Will; and for ſuch meeting together and Praying before him, according to the Apoſtles Doctrine, and neither for Plotting, Contriving Inſurrections, or other dangerous Practices, theſe or any of them, not being ſo much as laid to our Charge; but if they could but find to the Number of Five of us, or above, ſometimes fewer, as may be perceived before, beſides thoſe of the Family, peaceably ſitting together, waiting upon the Lord, or the like num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber viſiting a Sick Friend or Neighbour, or doing the like Chriſtian, Humane and Neighbourly Duty, yet this was made occaſion great
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:98568:22"/>
enough for them to inform upon, and for ſome of the Juſtices (ſo called) to iſſue out Warrants upon, to take and to Spoil our Goods; yea, ſo great hath been the Envy of ſome of them (to wit, <hi>Joſeph Craddock</hi> and <hi>James Metcalfe,</hi> (as the Conſtables have reported) that they, or the one of them, to wit, <hi>Joſeph Craddock,</hi> hath commanded them (to wit, the ſaid Conſtables) <hi>To diſtrain what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Goods they found upon their Land, whom the Warrants were againſt, or in their Poſſeſſion, be it whoſe it would:</hi> So that if any Neighbours or Relation, in Compaſſion to the Sufferers, and their innocent Children, for their Suſtenance would have lent them a Cow to give them Milk to live upon, when their own was ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from them, or a Horſe or a Mare to ride upon, they have been affraid to do ſo by reaſon of ſuch Threatnings and of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions brought forth ſuitable to the ſame; for ſome were ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken upon the like account as the Mares from <hi>Stephen Winn</hi> and <hi>William Horner;</hi> though the Act by which they did pretend to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed, impoſeth the penalty of Diſtreſs upon the Goods and Chattels of none ſave upon the proper Goods and Chattels of the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der only; neither is the Land in this behalf a Debtor, or the Goods there upon lyable to diſtreſs, if not the Goods of the Offender, as aforeſaid. And hereby the Officers who had a mind to do wickedly have been Encouraged; and thoſe who had not a mind to do ſo wickedly, were ſometimes through fear compelled to take the Goods of others: as they did Yarn out of the Houſe of a Weaver, brought him to work, and Stuff already wrought for others, thereby miniſtring occaſion to People, ſeeing their Goods ſo taken from them to leave working with them, hereby endeavou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring as it were to ſtop Trading with them, and hinder a lively-hood or the Iſſues of Life from coming to them, and ſo are the men that in this caſe are found more Guilty of endeavouring to take Life then the <hi>Quakers,</hi> making the Informers Word and Oath, how falſe ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, a ſufficient ground for Conviction, and that without calling the partyes accuſed before them, to make their defence according to Law, and either to confeſs or deny the Fact. But this, though according to Reaſon, and to the Law both of Nature and of Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons they out-run; yet nevertheleſs for and notwithſtanding all the Spoil that this Informer <hi>Thornaby</hi> did make, and Goods he thus (as aforeſaid) got from Innocent People; and for and notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing all the aſſiſtance and encouragement that the ſaid <hi>Joſeph Crad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dock</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:98568:22"/>
and <hi>James Metcalfe</hi> offered him, ſuch was the Judgment of God upon him, that though he ſometimes (as was ſaid) got both the King's part and the Poor's part (as 'tis called) unto himſelf, yet inſtead of ſatisfying Debts, and growing Rich thereby, he run ſo far into Debt, and was active in ſo many Diſhoneſties, that he durſt not frequently, as formerly, ſhew his Face.</p>
               <p>And it is to be noted, that the ſaid <hi>William Thornaby</hi> the Elder coming upon a time, together with the Conſtable of <hi>Bainbrigg,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Honſe of one <hi>Dorothy Todd</hi> in the ſame <hi>Bainbrigg,</hi> where was a Meeting of the ſaid People in Scorn called <hi>Quakers,</hi> about his aforeſaid Wicked Enterprizes, where the Compiler of theſe Paper, was preſent; he the ſame Compiler was moved of the Lord to tell him, (to wit, the ſaid <hi>Thornaby) That the Lord God was intended, or would ſhortly bring a Ruin, Deſolation or Deſtruction upon him, and his Family or Houſe,</hi> or ſomething to that or the like purpoſe, as is remembred; which ſhortly after came to paſs; for he, to wit, the ſaid <hi>Thornaby</hi> never came in that place again; But his Wife being dead, as aforeſaid, and he by reaſon of his Debts, and other Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanours, not daring well to ſhew his face, as at other times, went for a time skulking up and down, being often obſerved to ſhift or remove in the Evening, which gave occaſion of bad ſuſpition to People; and at laſt the aforeſaid <hi>Ja. Metcalfe</hi> (one of his chief Props) being dead, as aforeſaid, he, to wit, the ſaid <hi>Thornaby</hi> Cheating an Exciſe-man of his Horſe, and other things, by borrowing the ſame of him, and going away there-with, as was reported, he went or removed himſelf up to <hi>London,</hi> and being come thither, applyed himſelf to the then Attourney General of the King (as was ſaid) Labouring with him to get all the remaining Fines (then ungot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, and which had been Charged, by reaſon of his Informations, and the Information of his Agents, as aforeſaid, upon ſeveral of the aforeſaid People called <hi>Quakers,</hi> Inhabiting in and about the places before-mentioned) Levied for; but failing of his Intent, or meeting with a Repulſe therein, he applyed himſelf in or about the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid City of <hi>London</hi> to a Bad, Diſhoneſt, Cheating kind of Life, as was ſaid; and after his continuing therein ſome time, at laſt dyed miſerably in Priſon, as was reported. And his Children being as it were deſpiſed with many for their Father's Acts, became ſcattered here and there, bearing the Reproach or Ignominy of their ſaid
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:98568:23"/>
Father's Diſhoneſty: And thus, or in like mannrr, as we are infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, was the End of this <hi>Thornaby.</hi> And his Son young <hi>William Thornaby</hi> yet remains as we hear, leading a Life not much unlike the Practices he learned of his Father, as we are informed. All which might be ſufficient Cautions to forewarn all thoſe that remain from having a hand in ſuch like Actions, as theſe men before-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned (who are now gone) purſued, leſt they fall by that Hand, and come into the ſame Condemnation, and under the like Laſh and Reproach, as theſe men did.</p>
               <p>Nevertheleſs, the ſaid <hi>Joſeph Craddock</hi> yet remains, and not (as it ſeems) being content with the Wickedneſs he hath already committed againſt the Lord's People, neither taking that Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by other men's Harms as will be ſufficient to him, to make him beware what he doth in that behalf; but poſting on to the filling up of that meaſure of Wickedneſs that is yet behind; and being <hi>Commiſſary</hi> to the Biſhop of <hi>Cheſter,</hi> within the Arch-Deacony of <hi>Richmond,</hi> in the Dioceſs of <hi>Cheſter</hi> aforeſaid, hath himſelf or his Officers, or thoſe that act under the Umbrage of him, caſt ſeveral of the aforeſaid People called <hi>Quakers</hi> (being moſt of them of thoſe that ſuffered as aforeſaid) in Priſon at or near <hi>Richmond</hi> aforeſaid, upon Writs of <hi>Excommunicato Capiendo,</hi> to wit, <hi>Richard Robin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> of <hi>Counterſett, John Fothergill</hi> of <hi>Garr End</hi> and <hi>Chriſtopher Routh</hi> of <hi>Hawes,</hi> all in <hi>Wenſleydale,</hi> who were committed the 4th of the 11th moneth, 1678. and <hi>Stephen Winne</hi> and <hi>Richard Geldart</hi> both of <hi>Carleton</hi> in <hi>Coverdale,</hi> and two of the aforeſaid Sufferers, who were committed the 15th day of the 1ſt moneth laſt paſt, and moſt of them without being perſonally cited, or having any Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſerved on them, or ever hearing of that Proceed, until they were either Arreſted (as was <hi>John Fothergill, Stephen Winne</hi> and <hi>Richard Geldart)</hi> or within two dayes thereof (as was <hi>Richard Robinſon)</hi> the Cauſe of whoſe Commitment, as alledged by the Procurers thereof, or ſome of them, is as followeth, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſaid <hi>Richard Robinſon</hi> for Non-payment of an Aſſeſſment of 10 s. impoſed upon him towards the Repair of the Steeplehouſe at <hi>Askrigg,</hi> and other Matters joyned with the ſame, as Money for Deſtroying of <hi>Foxes,</hi> &amp;c. all which he could have paid ſave that for the Repair of the Steeplehouſe, if the ſame had been diſtrictly aſſeſſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:98568:23"/>
                  <hi>John Fothergill</hi> for an Aſſeſſment of 5 s. impoſed on him for the ſame Uſe, but never demanded on him (as he affirms) neither did he hear of the ſame until he was Arreſted, which was very Unjuſt. It had been but reaſonable to demand or acquaint the Party with what they expect from him, before they endeavour to puniſh for Non-payment of that which they never demanded of him.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Stephen Winne</hi> and <hi>Richard Geldart,</hi> for not going to the <hi>Steeple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe,</hi> nor receiving the <hi>Sacrament</hi> (ſo called) or ſome ſuch like things.</p>
               <p>And having thus impriſoned them, endeavour to make their Bonds as hard as they can or lies in their power, by Threatning the Goaler to keep them ſtrait; yet nevertheleſs the Juſt and Holy God is with them, and hath hitherto kept them from bowing or being bowed under them, or defiled with them; and He that hath hitherto kept them, we hope will ſtill be with them, ſo that we hope the Wicked One will not prevail over them, to make or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel them (notwithſtanding all their Endeavours) to do that which tends to the Defilement of their Conſciences, or leſſening of that Teſtimony which God in this behalf hath given unto them.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="discussion">
               <p>NOw it were convenient to diſcover what all thoſe Fines before mentioned, for which the Diſtreſſes ſince the beginning of the year 1670. were taken did amount to, to the intent it might appear, whether thoſe Perſons before mentioned (to wit, <hi>Joſeph Craddock, James Metcalfe, Thomas Craddock,</hi> and the reſt, that made themſelves ſo Active in the Matters aforeſaid, have dealt truly with the King and the Poor, in rendring to each their reſpective Parts of the ſame; but being that we cannot do the ſame, becauſe the Quantity of all the ſaid Fines ſo diſtrained for hath not as yet (that we remember) come to our Knowledge, neither know we how all the Goods were by thoſe that diſtrained the ſame ſold, therefore ſhall caſt up as near as we can the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:98568:24"/>
true Value and Worth of the ſaid Goods; according to that Eſtimate that the Owners of them have reſpectively given in, and do find them upon Examination to amount (beſides the Diſtreſſes taken in the Town of <hi>Richmond)</hi> to about the ſum of 234 l. 9 s. 8 d.</p>
               <p>Beſides paid by <hi>James Calvert</hi> of <hi>Burton</hi> 10 l. which in the whole will make the ſum of 244 l. 9 s. 8 d.</p>
               <p>Now ſeeing the King was by the Act of Parliament to have one Third Part of the ſaid Fines, and the Poor another Third Part, the Queſtion will be, <hi>How much of the aforeſaid Sum they ſeverally got?</hi> for it cannot be rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonably expected, but that the Value of the Diſtreſs ſo taken, being great, the Fines for which the ſame was taken (though we cannot acertain them all, becauſe we know them not all) muſt alſo be Conſiderable.</p>
               <p>But for the Town of <hi>Richmond;</hi> we find that the Fines for which thoſe Diſtreſſes there taken were levyed, do amount to the Sum of 57 l. 5 s. that 20 l. which <hi>Rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard Dawſon</hi> was ſaid to pay for the Goods taken from <hi>John Chaytor,</hi> and which his Widow after his Death reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, either in Quantity, Quality or Worth, being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>And then out of this Sum of 55 l. 5 s.—</item>
                  <item>The King's Part will be 18 l. 8 s. 4 d.</item>
                  <item>The Poor's Part—18 l. 8 s. 4 d.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The Queſtion will be, <hi>How this laſt was paid?</hi> which <hi>Thomas Craddock</hi> and the Officers concerned muſt An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="testimonial">
            <pb n="47" facs="tcp:98568:24"/>
            <p>THe <hi>Compiler</hi> of theſe Papers did receive the Account of all the Sufferings within mentioned (but what himſelf was a Wineſs of, or Sufferer in) from the hands or by the Information of the Sufferers themſelves, or ſuch Perſons as were appointed by them, or took it upon them to collect and make known the ſame; and is now, after ſeveral Examinations thereof, as to the Truth of it, committed to publick view, and owned by us whoſe Names are hereunto ſubſcribed, and who were Witneſſes of, or concerned in ſome part or other of the ſame Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings and Paſſages, as a true Teſtimony and Relation of the ſame.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <list>
                     <item>Richard Routh,</item>
                     <item>Richard Binks,</item>
                     <item>Thomas Whitton,</item>
                     <item>Oſwald Routh,</item>
                     <item>Richard Robinſon,</item>
                     <item>John Key,</item>
                     <item>Thomas Johnſon,</item>
                     <item>Robert Cutter,</item>
                     <item>John Chaytor,</item>
                     <item>James Janſon,</item>
                     <item>James Longſtaff,</item>
                     <item>William Horner.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>now Priſoners.</head>
                     <item>Stephen Winne,</item>
                     <item>Chriſtopher Routh,</item>
                     <item>John Fothergill,</item>
                     <item>Richard Geldart,</item>
                     <item>Richard Robinſon,</item>
                  </list>
               </signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
